<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The application of the lavves of England for Catholike priesthood and the Sacrifice of the Masse. Directed to the lords of his Maiesties most honourable priuie counsell, iudges, iustices, and other studients of the law.</title>
            <author>Pendryck, William, 1583-1650.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 165 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21070</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7435</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117587</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852799</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852799</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18148</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21070)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18148)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 832:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The application of the lavves of England for Catholike priesthood and the Sacrifice of the Masse. Directed to the lords of his Maiesties most honourable priuie counsell, iudges, iustices, and other studients of the law.</title>
                  <author>Pendryck, William, 1583-1650.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 45 [i.e. 95], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[H. Jaye],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Cullen [i.e. Mechlin] with licence :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini. M.DC.XXIII. [1623]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint false; actual place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Title page verso has errata; text of preface begins: 'It was euer the craft and subtilty of the Heathen' .. This is probably the later issue, with A4 apparently by a different printer.--STC.</note>
                  <note>At end: initials 'M.E.', i.e. reverse initials of Eliseus of St. Michael, name in religion of William Pendryck.--STC.</note>
                  <note>Final numbered page misnumbered 45.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18148:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18148:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE APPLICATION OF THE LAVVES OF ENGLAND FOR CA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THOLIKE PRIESTHOOD, And the Sacrifice of the Maſſe. <hi>DIRECTED TO THE LORDS of his Maieſties moſt Honourable priuie Counſell, Judges, Juſtices, and other Studients of the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Mentita eſt iniquitas ſibi. </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi>
26.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>O violentia veritatis, quod ſemper illa tenuit, inimicorum confeſſio confirmauit.</hi> 
               </p>
               <bibl>Aug. cont. Donatiſt. poſt col. cap. 3.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at CVLLEN with Licence, Anno Domini. M.DC.XXIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:18148:2"/>
            <head>The Printer to the Reader.</head>
            <p>GEntle Reader, this litle Treatiſe falling by chaunce into my hands, I of my ſelfe (the Author thereof being vnknowne vnto me) thought it worthy of thy view; but by reaſon of an vncorrected originall written Copie, and eſpecially my ſelfe being vnskilfull of the Engliſh tongue, many errours and omiſſions haue happened, not onely in the Orthographie but alſo in the ſetting downe the alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations ſomewhat indiſtinctly, and in falſe pointing. Therefore I hope (theſe cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances duly conſidered) thou wilt be pleaſed in reading ouer this Treatiſe, to correct them with thy pen: whereof the greater faults are (after the Printing here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) gathered by a friend, and ſet downe in manner as followeth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faults eſcaped.</head>
            <p>PAge 5. in the title, for generall Councels, read, Councels.
<hi>Ibid.</hi> line 20. Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, read Antichriſt was. <hi>Ibid.</hi> l.
21. fled, r. flight. p. 6. l. 17. which, r. with. p. 8. l. 17. Can. 18. r. Can.
1. p. 9. l. 19. fift, r. faſt. <hi>Ibid.</hi> l. 26. your, r. the. p. 10. l.
27. 39<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. r. 413. pa. 11. l. 25. Can. 1. r. Can. 5. p. 12. l. 5. where, r. were.
<hi>Ibid.</hi> l. 13. words of the, r. words of conſecration ſome. p. 13. l. 14. Retentine, r. Retentiue. p. 14. l. 5. in the auncient, r. from the auncient. <hi>Ibid.</hi> title teſtaments, r. teſtimonies. p. 16. l. 10. who, r. of whom. <hi>Ibid.</hi> l. 22. is God, r. to God, p. 17. l. 17. terme, r. forme. p. 20 l. 12. that beſides, r. beſides. p. 22. l. 27. died, r. liued. p. 23. l. 23. Ino, r. Iuo. <hi>Ibid.</hi> l. 27. 111. r. 91. p. 32. l.
18. 03. r. 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. p. 36. l. 15. and ſo much, r. and that ſo much. p. 37. l.
7. nor, r. not. p. 38. l. 10. haſhly, r. raſhly. p. 39. l. 5. Abbots. And, r. Abbots according to D. Doue. <hi>Ibid.</hi> l. 23. theretofore, r. heretofore. <hi>Ibid.</hi> l. 27. 86. r. 176. p. 10. l. 7. 165. r. 105. p. 43. l. 25. nor, r. or. p. 45. l. 6. very, r. euery. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0. Col. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>48. r. Col.
748. p. 49. l. 22. Angelorum, r. Anglorum. p. 58. l. 2. firſt 100. r. 1000.
<hi>Ibid.</hi> l. 22. odder, r. odde. p. 61. l. 17. Reioined, r. Reioiner. p.
64. l. 15. grates, r. gates. p. 65. l. 23. onwardly, r. outwardly. p. 67. l.
27. blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemours, r. blaſphemous. p. 70. throughout, for Biſhops, read Fathers. <hi>Ibid.</hi> l. 15. 819. r. 870. <hi>Ibid.</hi> l. 18. 1000. r. 900.
<hi>Ibid.</hi> l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>9. the 2. <hi>Lateran</hi> vnder In. 2. Fa. 1200. p. 72. l.
14. <hi>Toſtanis,</hi> r. <hi>Toſtatus.</hi> p. 75. l. 4. of the authority, r. the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. <hi>Ibid.</hi> l. 17. to iudggment, r. to the iudgement p.
76. l. 7. hence it is that the, r. hence is the. p. 77. l. 13. Maieſtie giue, r. Maieſtie p. 11. giue p. 81. l. 1. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. r. <hi>lib.</hi> 1.
<hi>ibid.</hi> l. 12. 23. r. 25. <hi>Ibid.</hi> l. 22. litle a like, r. like a little. p. 84. l. 4. to his effect, r. to this effect. p. 86. l. 3. the might, r. might. <hi>Ibid.</hi> l. 26. as once, r. but once. p. 88. l. 17. it was, was it.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Faults eſcaped in the Margent.</head>
               <p>Page 3. at Preſcription Fol 149. <hi>Ibid.</hi> at Limitation Fol. 126. <hi>Ibid.</hi> at diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion Fol. 67. p. 9. Pactio in ſene Prat. in Serie. p. 10. for Suicio, read ſub Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicio. <hi>Ibid</hi> 398. r.
413. p. 14. Petent r. Retent p. 18. Ormerod pa. r. Orm. fol. 3. pr.
<hi>Ibid.</hi> Cal. 1 1. c. 1. r. Cal. l. 1. c. 14. p. 23. Chemnit. pa. 3. r. Chemnit. pa. 93. p. 24. Cyrill. Hier. Catch. 4. miſt. p. 33. col. 2441. r. col. 1294. p Cent. 4. Col. 291. p. 47. Bal. cent. 1. fol. 3. p. 49. Holmiſt lib. 1. r. Hol. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. pa. 102. p. 51. fol. 137. r. 173. p. 54. Sect. 146. r. Sect. 164. p. 77. Caſt. in defenſ. tranſl. p. 170. p. 81. for Gen. v. 2. r. Gen. v. 11. p. 87. Couel. pag. 77. p. 78. Powel pag. 70. p 91. Whit. c. 18. r. Whit. rat. 8.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the Table.</head>
               <p>Page 96: twelue generall, read twelue Councels.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:18148:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE. </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable Lords, wiſe Iudges, and other Learned Lawyers.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was euer the craft and ſubtilty of the <hi>Heathen,</hi> but much more of the <hi>Apoſtates</hi> and <hi>Heretickes,</hi> when they deadly hated and perſecuted the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Chriſtians,</hi> and ſpecially Gods <hi>Prieſts,</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the guides, and Paſtors of that Flocke, they ſought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy) to ſound their diſgraces into credulous eares, and charge them of diſloialty towards their Prince and Magiſtrate, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to make them odious to their Princes, and hatefull to the Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>So did that Magitian of Aegipt, leaſt his deceipts ſhould haue beene impugned by the Chriſtians, accuſe them before the Emperour
<hi>Valerian,</hi> who (as <hi>Euſebius</hi> doth report) was ſo fauourable to the Catholick Christians, in the beginning of his raigne, that he would not permit any perſon ſhould wrong them. So did ſome wicked perſons about the Emperour <hi>Aurelian,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke him to perſecute the Chriſtians generally throughout all the confines of his Empire; who notwithſtanding had moſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly (as appeareth by the Writings of <hi>Euſebius ad Oroſius</hi>) vſed them in the firſt ſixe yeares of his raigne. So was holy <hi>Athanaſius</hi> brought before the Arrian Emperours and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and accuſed of <hi>Nigromancie, Adulterie,</hi> and <hi>Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie.</hi> So was the Clergie condemned to death, and exile vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <pb facs="tcp:18148:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb facs="tcp:18148:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb facs="tcp:18148:4"/> 
               <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtate, vnder pretence of diuers crimes, and namely of ſedition falſly forged againſt them. So did the <hi>Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dales</hi> being Heretickes, extreamely plague the Catholickes in <hi>Affrick,</hi> accuſing them that they had ſecret conference by Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, and Letters with the
<hi>Romanes</hi> againſt them. And by this meanes did the Empereſſe
<hi>Theodora,</hi> a woman of the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichian</hi> hereſie, cruelly perſecute the Pope <hi>Siluerius,</hi> and the Clergie, vnder the colour of ſome Letters intercepted by her Councell, whereby the Catholick Christians ſhould haue called in the <hi>Gothes</hi> &amp; forraigne powers, to inuade the Citie of Rome and the Empire.</p>
            <p>Yet this ſhamefull ſubtilty and crafty deceipt, was neuer ſo notoriouſly vſed by the <hi>Pagans,</hi> the <hi>Arrians,</hi> the
<hi>Gothes,</hi> the <hi>Vandals,</hi> the <hi>Lumbards,</hi> the
<hi>Donatiſts,</hi> &amp;c. as in the late perſecutions and practiſes of Protestant Miniſters, eſpecially in <hi>England</hi> againſt the
<hi>Catholicks,</hi> in their Pamphlets and Pulpits, vrging the State to ſuppreſſe them with death, ſeuere exilements, and edicts, as if they had beene ſo many <hi>Catilines</hi> towards their <hi>Senate,</hi> and ſo many <hi>Abſolons</hi> towards their <hi>Dauid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The long time of our perſecution: the number of them that were afflicted: the diuerſity of their rankes and qualities, and their humours and diſpoſitions: the perpetuity and variety of temptations and tribulations: the infinite indignities ſuffered by the mercileſſe ſearching and robbing of Purſeuants, Promoters, Informers, and ſuch needy Officers (who cared not by whoſe fall they roſe) (not hauing deſerts or other degrees to clime to <pb facs="tcp:18148:4"/> the height of their ambition.) We paſſed thorough for ſo many yeares; if they had fallen out among any other conſtitution of men then <hi>Catholiks,</hi> they might haue wrung (very probably) out of men well mortified, and patient, ſome action of diſlike and diſcontentment, ſeeing <hi>Triſtia pro virtute tollerare,</hi> to endure heauy things for vertues ſake is a point hard to be practiſed. But yet neuertheleſſe, what hath beene our fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity towards our Prince, and behauiour towards our Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, with all humility, reſpect, modeſty, and ſubiection? euer either readily doing what they enioyned, or patiently ſuffering what they impoſed; <hi>Fiant inimici noſtri Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> Let our enemies be our Iudge therein: and let the Roles, Regiſters, and Recordes ſpeake. The true reaſon whereof was the doctrine, for by the Religion which we profeſſe, we are taught, that we muſt obey our Princes <hi>Non propter itam, ſed propter conſcientiam,</hi> not for any indignation, but for conſcience ſake; and that to reſiſt them, is to reſist Gods ordinances. And this is the bit and bridle that euery true Catholicke carieth in his mouth, to reſtraine him from that by grace and feare of Gods iudgements, which fleſh and bloud otherwiſe with the liuely ſence and feeling of inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable miſeries and afflictions, might driue him vnto.</p>
            <p>And if ſome of vs, forgetting our beſt fortunes at home, did flie from the ſtorme of perſecution, into a place of refuge, (taking ſuch helpes as the charity of other Countries affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) and there perfected in the courſe of vertue and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, returned into <hi>England:</hi> our onely intent was (as <pb facs="tcp:18148:5"/> heauen and earth ſhall witneſſe with vs at the dreadfull day of Doome) to win ſoules from misbeliefe, and with the ſweat of our browes (yea of our deareſt bloud) to gleane a fewe eares, the ſilly reliques of their infortunate Harueſt, who had miſled infinite ſoules into endleſſe perdition. Alas, what is <hi>Prieſthood</hi> now, that was not in former times? that it muſt be accounted in theſe our dayes
<hi>treacherous,</hi> which hath euer beene reputed both in Parliament, and elſe-where, the moſt honourable calling next to the Prince, as the places of our great Priests and Archbiſhops beare euidence? Nothing is or can be changed in that <hi>Sacrament:</hi> howſoeuer, the mindes and proceedings of Protestants doe change. Neither did or doth the Pope or any other Biſhop by making vs Priests, claime or get any more authority in <hi>England;</hi> then they of <hi>Geneua</hi> or <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Proteſtant Ministers. And as for oathes and promiſes in receiuing holy <hi>Orders,</hi> wee neither take nor plight any but one common to the <hi>Prieſts</hi> of all Nations, which is a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne vow of perpetuall chaſtity, a thing rather pleaſant then offenſiue to vertuous mindes. But Gods true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on being abandoned out of our miſerable Countrey through our ſinnes, the honour of God, and reuerent reſpect of his ſacred <hi>Prieſts</hi> was gone withall: and in ſteed of Priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Prerogation graunted to them by diuine and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Lawes, they haue beene moſt ſubiect to iniuries, vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies, contempt, and calumnies, of all conditions and ſtates of the Realme. But if the glorious Doctor St. <hi>Auguſtine <pb facs="tcp:18148:5"/> Epiſt.
212.</hi> might haue beene heard, theſe imputations had not receiued ſuch credit againſt them: for thus he ſaith to <hi>Pancarius</hi> an Officer, and honourable perſon, before whom a certaine Priest named
<hi>Secundarius</hi> was accuſed of a great crime. <hi>Quod videntur obiicere Presbitero, &amp;c. The crime wherewith they change their Prieſt, muſt be looked vnto, ſo alwayes if thoſe that be his accuſers be Catholickes: for againſt a Catholick Prieſt wee neither can, nor ought to admit the accuſation of Heretickes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſeeing it now pleaſeth our gracious <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> to conſider our eſtate, and with the eyes of his Peereleſſe cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie to looke vpon vs ſo long, and ſo dangerous ſicke (of the late
<hi>Queenes</hi> euill) whom no Phyſick can cure, but the ſacred hands of his annoynted <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> nor no <hi>Salue</hi> can heale, but the ſoueraine <hi>Balme</hi> of his renowned clemencie; And ſo to qualifie our former preſſours, permitting vs <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edere buccellam noſtram ſine dolore,</hi> to put a bit of meate into our mouthes without ſorrow, without frights, without flights, and without circumuentions of our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries.</p>
            <p>Wherefore moſt Honorable, Reuerend, Graue, and Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<hi>Patrones</hi> (for I doe preſume to challenge this title at your hands) vouchſafe to aſſist now our gracious Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne in this his Royall diſpoſition, and call to minde your Predeceſſours, who (being Religious, wiſe, learned, poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique, and diſcreete, and therefore dignified by our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes <pb facs="tcp:18148:6"/> Catholick Progenitours) did leaue you to ſucceede them not onely in their ſincerity of Iustice, and fidelity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Princes, but likewiſe in their Religion towards God: The law of nature, the law of Nations, the law of <hi>England</hi> it ſelfe (in that ſtate it is) requireth it; the law of God calleth vpon you, and bringeth euidence of this your obligation; your promiſe to God, to his Church, when you were first borne bindeth you: So many of your noble compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie as are admitted to the Honourable Order of the <hi>Garter,</hi> haue (or ought to haue) ſworne it: you are all Councellours or Officers to his Maiestie, which by title of inheritance, and at his Coronation, by the Oath and Fidelity of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Prince, hath obliged himſelfe to maintaine it: of that which is his office, your places profeſſe performance; your promiſe to God, obedience and voluntary ſubmiſſion to his Church, fidelity to Prince, duty to Countrey, compaſſion to the vniuſt oppreſſed daily call vpon you to ſee it done.</p>
            <p>Pardon Noble <hi>Patrons,</hi> if peremptorily without all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception I demaund but iuſtice by the preſent forcible Lawes of
<hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who, for his better ſatisfaction, deſireth to ſee theſe enſuing points at length: then reade that moſt worthy and laborious Treatiſe, entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led:</hi> The Proteſtants Apologie for the Romane Church.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="section">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18148:6"/>
            <head>SECTION. I. THE LAVV TEARMES IN GENERALL PERVSED IN THIS OVR APPLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CATION. </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONORABLE, REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend, Graue, and Learned.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>EING your ſelues are as it were, the principall paſſages vnder his Maieſtie, in, and by which is tranſported, whatſoeuer is done in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Iuſtice. In which courſe, of your great and weighty Imployment, as you are continually occaſioned, and ſomtimes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuned, Iudiciouſly to obſerue and diſcerne both of cauſes, &amp; perſons brought in queſtion before you: So are there none, whome necceſsity hath ſo <pb n="2" facs="tcp:18148:7"/> much prouoked, to become in this kinde your hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Suppliants, as are the dailie deiected, diſgraced, &amp; impouerished Catholikes</p>
            <p>And for as much, as Religion is the matter of their calamity, we haue preſumed bereby, (with all humble remo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrance) in their behalfe, to commend the ſame, vnto the ſerious, and retired view of your leaſurable, iudicious, &amp; graue Conſiderations. The which alſo we do with more confident, (I confeſſe) &amp; peculiar reſpect, in that the method, &amp; grounds of proofe, which shalbe obſerued, and proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, throughout this our humble Application, are in them ſelues correſpondent, to the like receiued principles of your owne lawes, and as being ſuch, do therefore after a more then ordinary manner, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate them ſelues to your iudgment.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">An ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult &amp; obſcure words &amp; termes of the lawes of this Realme printed A 1602 Fol 25. Fol 26.</note>For if I miſtake not, but do rightly informe my ſelfe from your booke of <hi>The termes of the law:</hi> your procedings in caſe of Attainder are threefold: as by <hi>Outlary,</hi> where the partie doth not appeare to anſwere the law: by <hi>Verdict,</hi> which is the triall of honeſt <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors,</hi> vpon his appearing to anſwere the law: and by
<hi>Confeſsion,</hi> which is the parties owne acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his offence Alſo in caſe of <hi>Title</hi> to tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall poſſeſsions, there be certaine receaued grounds in your law of great force to demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrate the right as faire, ancient, &amp; vnſuſpected <hi>Euidence,</hi> the
<hi>Teſtimony</hi> 
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:18148:7"/> of credible witneſſes, and euen
<hi>Praeſcription</hi> it ſelfe, where of no memory occurreth to the contrary. In ſo much as by the ſtatute of <hi>Limitation,</hi> no man is inhabled to commence, &amp; proſecute ſuite,<note place="margin">Fol.
140</note> for any landes, whereof him ſelfe, or his Anceſtors, haue not bene before ſeiſed, within a certaine time in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe limited: The only <hi>Priority</hi> of <hi>poſſeſsion</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing alſo this fauour in your law, that to the partie diſſeiſed of ſuch his
<hi>poſſeſsion,</hi> you afford ſpeciall remedy, by <hi>VVritt</hi> of Aſsiſe,<note place="margin">Fol 24. Fol. 47. Fol. 47.</note> allowing him alſo the benefit of his <hi>Continuall Claime,</hi> to preuent
<hi>Deſcent</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other parties dying ſeiſed. Moreouer where the letter of your <hi>Statute law</hi> appeareth to be in ſome caſes doubtfull, you are reported to hold that ſenſe, and vnderſtanding thereof for moſt reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which is found moſt agreable, with the knowne anſwerable <hi>Practiſe</hi> of enſewing times.</p>
            <p>Beſides all this, there are eſtablished with you, for the finall ending of all ariſing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſies <hi>High cours of Iudgment</hi> to giue <hi>definitiue ſentence,</hi> and the ſame ſo giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not by the law it ſelfe but by your ſelues placed, as Iudges to pronounce, &amp; determine what is the law: Againſt which ſentence ſo once or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly giuen,
<hi>No VVritt of errour,</hi> or <hi>Appeale</hi> lieth,<note place="margin">Fol.
82.</note> whereby to ſupport the partie ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uicted, in the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther humor of his vnſatisfied and endles conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Of all which I haue informed my ſelf, partly <pb n="4" facs="tcp:18148:8"/> from your foreſaid booke of <hi>the Termes of the law,</hi> and ſome by conference with others. So as I am to craue pardon, if exceeding herein the boldneſſe of my profeſsion, I haue miſtaken, or not dewly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued the apte proprietie of wordes, retaining yet (I hope) the ſubſtance of the matter.</p>
            <p>And for as much, as theſe your ciuill obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, preſcribed for the inquiry, &amp; ſetting forth of right, are in themſelues no other, then as liuely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblances, &amp; imitations of thoſe maine grounds, which facred Theologie affordeth, to the demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Truth: I am now likewiſe to craue fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leaue, to entreate you of your ſerious, &amp; retired view, of your leaſurable, Iudicious, and graue conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, of this our short <hi>Application,</hi> of ſome prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall parts thereof, to the like anſwerable grounds, and principles, ſo plentifully abounding, in proofe of our Catholike Religion. But leaſt I should be tedions to your honors attention, I will but ſet downe one point, for the which Catholikes are ſo often commanded, to appeare before your honors to anſwere to the law, &amp; are dailie deiected, diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced &amp; Impouerished: The point is knowne to you all, to witt, for entertaining of Maſsing Prieſts.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="section">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:18148:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECTION. II.</hi> A verdict conſiſting of twelue generall Councels, al of them being within the firſt foure hundred &amp; od yeares after our Sauiour Chriſt.</head>
            <p>FIrſt therfore, concerning your proceeding by <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors:</hi> if that may be eſteemed to be a true <hi>Verdict,</hi> which is ſo, by ſuch giuen, you haue then here the ſame, giuen in the fore ſaid point (which might be giuen in other points likewiſe of our Catholike Faith,) by the Ancient Fathers, who being aſſembled in Generall Councells, &amp; Synodes, &amp; ſworne vpon the perill of their ſoules, haue in this, &amp; other many ſpeciall caſes directly found for vs. &amp; to that effect, that thoſe of our <hi>Iury,</hi> may be the leſſe ſuſpected of you, we will bring them of the firſt 400. yeares after Chriſt, the which Ages, euen your owne Doctors being Iudges, were freeſt from all corruption, &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the true Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; Faith deliuered by the Apoſtles D. Fulke in his Anſwere to a counterfaite Catholike pag. 36. ſaith. <hi>The Religion of the Papistes came in, &amp; preuailed the yeare of God:</hi> Anno
607, in the which time (ſaith he) <hi>The Reuelation of Antichriſt with the Church fled in to the wilderneſſe to witt</hi> in A<hi rend="sup">o.</hi> 607. And Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de Voyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one of your Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te Doctors,<note place="margin">Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de Voyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his epiſt. to the Reader.</note> in his diſcourſe vpon the Catalogue of Doctors, in the Epiſtle to the Reader, <hi>poſt medium;</hi> affirmeth,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18148:9"/> 
               <hi>that Anno</hi> 605. <hi>VVhen Pope Boniface was enſtalled in the Papall throne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Powell pa. 105</note>
               <hi>then falſhood gott the victory.</hi> And M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Gabriel Powell, in his Conſiderations of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts reaſons ſaith: <hi>I grant that from the yeare of Chriſt</hi> 605. <hi>The profeſſant Companie of Poperie hath bene very viſible and perſpicuous.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Perkins
307.</note> And M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Perkins in his expoſition of the Creed affirmeth:
<hi>That during the ſpace of</hi> 900. <hi>yeares the Popiſh hereſie hath ſpread it ſelfe ouer the whole earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Whit. p.
35.</note> And M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Whitaker <hi>de Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſto contra Sanderum,</hi> ſaith: <hi>During all that time</hi> (to witt of 600. yeares,) <hi>The Church was pure and flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, and inuiolably taught, &amp; defended the faith, deliuered from the Apostles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the like acknowledgement is made by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other learned Proteſtants which were tedions to your honors,<note place="margin">In his booke of Inſtitut ſet out in fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch printed at Gene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ua 1562.</note> to ſett downe in this our short. <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</hi> Only we will conclude which Caluine your cheife man: who albeit he doth not graunt the flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing eſtate of the Romane Church, the full ſpace of the firſt. 600. yeares, after Chriſt, yet doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that no cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of Faith was made vntill the times of <hi>S. Auguſtine, Epiphanius, Optatus, &amp;c.</hi> which was for
440. yeares after Chriſt, Theſe be his owne wordes in his booke of Inſtitutions ſet forth in French: <hi>It was athing</hi> (ſaith he)
<hi>notorions &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt, that after the Apoſtles age, vntil thoſe times, no change was made in doctrine, neither at Rome, nor at other citties.</hi> Thus Caluine.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:18148:9"/>Therefore hauing freed our iury from all ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, euen our enemies being our Iudges,<note place="margin">Whitg. in his defence p. 330.</note> we wil pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce as <hi>Fore-man</hi> of our
<hi>Iury,</hi> that notable and famous <hi>Councell of Nice;</hi> the which (ſaith M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Whitgift a proteſtante writer,) is of al wiſe, &amp; learned men reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced, eſteemed, &amp; embraced next vnto the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures themſelues.<note place="margin">The 1. Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell of Nice. can. 3.</note> This Councell was celebrated the yeare of Chriſt 325. at the which was preſent
318. Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops, who did decree, that Prieſts that did ſay Maſſe, &amp; offer ſacrifice,<note place="margin">It is not let at liberty to marry, becauſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception is taken at wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men but the mother, etc</note> should not keepe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie with any woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but with their mother, ſiſter, fathers ſiſters, and mothers ſiſters; but should liue chaſte,<note place="margin">And in the <hi>14</hi> Canon. it makes mention of Priests that do ſacrifice</note> as S. Baſile expoundeth this Canon, in his Epiſt. to Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corius.<note place="margin">Epi.ſtry.</note> As appeareth in the third Canon, and acknowledged by all the Doctors of your Church. And not only this point, is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by this Councell,<note place="margin">Theod. li 1 hiſt. cap. 8. Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na de Baptiſ. Can 69. ca. 10. ca. 11.</note> but likewiſe ſundry others As 1. vnwritten Traditions 2. that the Sacraments by the inſtitution of Chriſt do conferre grace. 3. that extreame Vnction was a Sacrament. The Reall preſence, Indulgences, with many other points of Catholike Doctrine, maintained to this day in the Church of Rome</p>
            <p>Your honors then do ſee, that this Councell <pb n="8" facs="tcp:18148:10"/> which we haue placed as <hi>Fore-man,</hi> is altogether for vs, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning Catholike Prieſthood, &amp; many other points of Religion in controuerſy at this day.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Conc. Arelat. An. 330</note>For the ſecond
<hi>Iuror</hi> we shall place the Councell holden at Arles, called Arelatenſe Concilium, cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated shortly after the Nicene Councell, as ſome do thinke, Anno 330. in the 2. &amp; 3. Canon, doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibite the marriage of Prieſts, &amp; therefore is repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by Szegedin, a proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t writer. This Prieſthood, can be vnderſtood of no other Prieſthood,<note place="margin">In locis com. p. 327.</note> then the Catholike Prieſthood, our aduerſaries being Iudges; With many other points of Catholike Doctrine, making moſt of thoſe Canons, out of the Nicene Councell: a manifeſt proofe, that the Nicene Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uncell did not leaue the matter at libertie, of prieſts marriage.</p>
            <p>The third Iury man shall be the Romane Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell Anno 324, Can.
81. the which maketh mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Cardinals, Bisſhops, Prieſts, Deacons, Subdeacons, Aco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lytes, Exorciſtes, Readers, and Doore-keepers,</hi> The which ſacred Orders, are no where to be found, but in our Catholike Church. Which is acknowledged by the Centurywriters, Cent. 4. col. 873. me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> much eſteemed of, by the Church of England, &amp; diſclaimed by others, as by M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Fulke, in his Retentiue, in theſe words:<note place="margin">pag. 67.</note> 
               <hi>VVith all our hart we defie abhorre detest, &amp; spit at your greaſie Antichriſtian Orders,</hi> But you may ſee by <pb n="9" facs="tcp:18148:10"/> theſe his wordes, that he is vnmindfull of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie of theſe ſacred Orders.</p>
            <p>The <hi>fourth of our Iury,</hi> shalbe the Councell of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocaeſarea holden Anno 314. and approued by the Councel of Nice, which doth decree Can. 1.<note place="margin">Can. 1.</note> 
               <hi>That Prieſts who do marry, ſhould be depoſed of their charge,</hi> with many other things concerning maners &amp; good life.</p>
            <p>The fift of our <hi>Iury</hi> is the Councel of <hi>Laodicea</hi> cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated about the yeare 364. The which decreed Can. 13. that the Prieſt should not bee elected by the people.<note place="margin">Pacteo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus in Sene Concil.</note> Alſo Can 19. concerning certaine Rites in publicke ſeruice time, as namely ſome prayers in ſilence, others pronounced, then the Pax (or kiſſe of peace) to be giuen, and the oblation to be offered; And Can.
21. That the Subdeacon might not enter into the <hi>Veſtry</hi> and handle the holy veſſells. And Can. 48. that the Baptiſed after Baptiſme should receaue holy Chriſme. And Can. 50. the fift of lent: and an. 52. not to marry in lent: All the which Canons <hi>Oſiander</hi> a learned proteſtant diſclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes from, &amp; rebukes bitterly albeit vndeſeruedly.<note place="margin">Oſiand. Cent. 4. p 393.</note> Now if this Councell maketh for vs Catholikes, or you of the Church of England, I Appeale to your graue Iudgment and ſerious conſiderations.</p>
            <p>The Sixt of our <hi>Iury</hi> is your Councell called
<hi>Elibertinum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anno 305.</note> no leſſe antcient then the fore ſaid <pb n="10" facs="tcp:18148:11"/> Councells; this Councell: can. 27, &amp; can. 33. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed moſt plainlie againſt prieſtes, who marry af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they haue taken vpon them prieſthood; This Councell was celebrated about the yeare 305 in Spaine; The which Councell the Doctors of your Church vſe to obiect againſt Catholikes concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Images, miſtaking the intention of the Councell.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anno 396. ſub Suiciovt quidem volunt.</note>The Seuenth of our <hi>Iury</hi> is the 2. Councell of of Carthage Anno 386 wherat S. Auſtine was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent &amp; ſubſcribed therto which doubted not in like manner to ground this point vpon antiquitie, and the Apoſtles doctrine; ſo that in the 2. Canon. it ſaith theſe wordes: <hi>Omnibus placet &amp;c</hi> In pleaſeth vs all, that Bishops<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Prieſts, and Deacons, &amp;c, shall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteine from wiues, which the Apoſtles did teach and Antiquitie did keepe, let vs likewiſe obſerue; &amp; many other points doth this Councell decree for Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liks.</p>
            <p>The eight of our <hi>Iury</hi> is the 3. Councell of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage celebrated in the yeare.<note place="margin">Anno 397.</note> 397. at the which like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe S. Auſtin was preſent &amp; ſubſcribed therto; alloweth of Confeſsion made to a Prieſte can. 32. and likewiſe of other points of Catholike doctrine, as of Purgatory. can. 29. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anno 398.</note>The 9. of our <hi>Iury</hi> is the 4. Councell of Cartha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge in the yeare 398. to the which ſubſcribed S.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18148:11"/> Auſtine being there preſent.<note place="margin">Aſoc. vult anno 418.</note> This Councell de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creeth can 5.6.7.8.9. for the inferior Orders of Readers, Exorciſt, Acolyth, doorkeepers, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons, further mentioning there according to the offices yet vſed, a booke of Exorciſmes for the Exorciſt, the Church lightes for the Accolite, pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, chalice, litle cruets full of water, and Towell for the prieſts handes: All which are confeſſed, and reproued by the Proteſtant writer Luke
<hi>Oſiander:</hi> in his Epitom. cent. 5. p. 4.</p>
            <p>The tenth of our <hi>Iury</hi> is the famous and Generall Councell of Epheſus celebrated about the yeare 431 by 200.<note place="margin">Anno
431.</note> Bishops which amongſt other Articles and points of our Cath doctrine ſaith in plaine wordes: <hi>Incruentam celebramus in Eccleſiis ſacrificii ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitutem:</hi> we do celebrate and offer vp in our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, an vnbloody ſacrifice: and in the wordes follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing approoues euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly the reall preſence,<note place="margin">Concil Nic. cap 10.</note> cauſing the Cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the Nicene Councell to be publickly read with theſe wordes.
<hi>Incruentum, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The eleuenth of our <hi>Iury</hi> is the firſt Toletane Councell in the yeare 405. which decreed can. 20.<note place="margin">Anno. 405. ſub.</note> for conſecration of Chriſme by a Bishop, and his ſending therof to the Prieſts, through his dioceſſe at eaſter yearly; Alſo can. 1. for the dailie offering Sacrifice, &amp;c to the great diſlike of the Proteſtant writer <hi>Oſiander:</hi> who ſaith therupon;<note place="margin">Cent. 5. p 46.</note> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <pb n="12" facs="tcp:18148:12"/> them to offer vp Sacrifice euery day.</p>
            <p>The twelft of our <hi>Iury</hi> is the Councell Mileui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane about the yeare 416.<note place="margin">Anno 416.</note> which decreed can. 12. that Maſſes prayers and ceremonies should not be vſed but ſuch as where allowed by the Councell, ſo doth the Councell of Chalcedon Anno 451. can.
15.</p>
            <p>The ſecond generall Councell of Nice in the 3. tom. act, 6. ſaith in moſt plaine termes: <hi>Neuer any of the Apostles or Fathers did call our vnbloody ſacrifice (meaning the maſſe) done in commemoration of the paſsion of our Sauiour, to be the ſigne or figure of his body: for he did not ſay, take you, eate you, the ſigne of my body, but take you eate you this my body, &amp;c: Albeit be ſore the wordes of the Fathers did call it</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſymbole or figure of his body: So plainly doth the 350. Bishops aſſembled in this Councell deliuer their ſentence in our behalf</p>
            <p>You ſee (Right honorable, Reuerend, Graue, and Learned Lords) the compleate number of our <hi>Iury,</hi> at whom no exceptions can be taken, euen the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of your Church being Iudges, they being all not only within the firſt 600. yeares, in which time was no corruption in Religion according to the confeſsion of many of our aduerſaries hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alleadged, but in the moſt florishing eſtate of the Church. Of which time your chiefe man Caluine ſaith: It was a matter out of all doubt, <pb n="13" facs="tcp:18148:12"/> that from the beginning euen vntill that time,<note place="margin">Lib. 4. Inſtit. cap. 2. §. 2.</note> (viz to S. Auſtins daies,) nothing was changed in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. Alſo in his booke of Inſtitutions in French printed at Geneua by
<hi>Conradus Badius</hi> Anno 1562. he ſaith expreſly: That it was a thing notorious &amp; without doubt, that after the Apoſtles age vntill thoſe times, no change was made in doctrine nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at Rome, nor at other citties. So plainely do our learned Aduerſaries acknowledge, that no change of faith was made by the Romane Church from the Apoſtles age vntill the time of S. Auſtin, Epiphanius, Optatus, &amp;c. which was 440. yeares after Chriſt, M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Fulke followeth his Maiſter Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine in this pointe ſaying in his
<hi>Retentine:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag 85.</note> The Popish church is but an Hereticall aſſembly, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from the vniuerſall church, long ſince Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtines departure ont of this life. This is the moſt common opinion of all Proteſtant writers, And thus much with your good fauours concerning the application of your terme of law called <hi>Verdict,</hi> which is the <hi>Triall of honeſt Iurors.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="section">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:18148:13"/>
            <head>SECTION. III. <hi>THE TESTAMENTI.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SECONDLY: if you reſpect <hi>VVitneſſes,</hi> you shall find all the Ancient Fathers for our cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, in ſo much that ſundry of our learned Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries doubt not therefore, to make generall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime in the ancient Fathers. Hence it is that M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Whitaker a Learned Proteſtant affirmeth: cont <hi>Duraen</hi> p. 423. The Popish Religion to be a patc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed couerlett of the Fathers errors,<note place="margin">In libel. vita I wely printed Londini pag 212. id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m Fulk. in his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. pag 55. Stratag Satanae li.
6. pag. 296</note> ſowed together. And that alſo M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> D. Humfrey did greuouſly re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prehend M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Iewell for his ſo bould appealing to the Fathers, affirming therefore of M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Iewell that herein he gaue the Papiſts to large a ſcope, that he was iniurious to himſelf, and after a manner ſpoiled himſelf, &amp; the church. And Iacobus Acontius in his Treatiſe, dedicated to Queene Elizab. ſpeaking of the bad ſucceſſe that Proteſtants writers had in citing the Fathers, exhorts them to for beare the citing of them ſaying: <hi>Equidem pernicioſiſsimam om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninoque fugiendam hanc eſſe arbitror conſuetudmem.</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly I hold this cuſtome viz of, &amp;c. to be very dangerous &amp; wholy to be auoyded viz: of citing the Fathers to the writers diſaduantage.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:18148:13"/>But for feare of ſuſpicion of our
<hi>VVitneſſes,</hi> we shall bring men ſo indifferent to our aduerſaries &amp; vs, that we may ſay of them, (as S. Auſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in like caſe diſputing againſt the <hi>Pelagians</hi> ſaith, of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers before his time:)<note place="margin">Auguſt. adu Iul. Pelag. lib. 2. prope fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem &amp; lib. 3. cap. 17. &amp; lib. 4. cap 12.</note> 
               <hi>Neque nobis neque vobis irati ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt, &amp;c They be angrie neither at you nor at vs: what they haue found in the Church, that they haue held: they haue taught, what they haue learned: and what they haue receaued from their Forefathers they haue deliured to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity.</hi> In ſo much as your owne learned writers are not wanting in their like anſwerable commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. Caluine ſpeaking of them ſaith: They in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, (ſpeaking of catholikes,<note place="margin">Caluin. Inſtit. lib. 4. cap. 2. Sect. 3.</note> alleadging Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,) ſett forth their churches very gloriouſly, &amp;c they report out of <hi>Irenaeus, Tertullian, Origen, Auguſtin, &amp; others, how highly they eſteemed this ſucceſsion</hi> wherto he there anſwereth &amp; giueth his like reaſon therof ſaying: conſidering it was a matter out of all doubt, that from the beginning vntill that time nothing was cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged in doctrine the holy Doctors tooke in argument that, which was ſufficient for the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing of all new errors: to witt, that they, viz, the Heretiques, oppugned the doctrine, which euen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the very Apoſtles themſelues had beene invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lably &amp; with one conſent retained. And M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Iewell a famous Proteſtant in his replye to M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Harding. pag. 266, ſaith. The godly Fathers, (meaning them <pb n="16" facs="tcp:18148:14"/> before S. Auſtins time,) ſought to the church of Rome, which then for puritie in Religion, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie in theſame, was moſt famous, aboue all others, this fore ſaid time was the firſt. 440, yeares after chriſt. Therfore for the further ſatisfaction of our aduerſaryes, wee shall bring for witneſſes euen them, who liued within the fore ſaid time, viz. within &amp; before S. Auguſtin his time.</p>
            <p>If need were, we might bring for witneſſes S. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew the Apoſtle;<note place="margin">In Epiſt. ad Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Achaiae cap. 1.</note> who in a booke made by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and written by his diſciples and generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued for authenticall by the whole Churche &amp; Chriſtian world, theſe wordes are recorded to haue beene ſpoken by himſelf: I daylie ſacrifice to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God the immaculate lamb, who notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtanding that he is truely ſacrificed, and his flesh truely eaten by the people, yet doth he ſtill remayne whole &amp; liuing.</p>
            <p>S. Clemens Epiſt 3, no prieſt ought to ſay maſk without the Bishops leaue. S. Martial Epiſt. ad Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>degalenſis. cap. 3. A ſacrifice is offered vpon the Altar is God the creator, not to man, or Angell Of the ſaid S. clement there is mention made in the Apoſtle S. Paule his Epiſtle to the Philippi. ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 4. verſ. 3. where he is numbred among the follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of S. Paul, and who was third Pope after S. Peter; who did write many things which he had o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:18148:14"/> verball tradition of the Apoſtles, who liued about the yeare. 80. The afore ſaid S. Martiall was ſent by Saint Peter into France, who afterwards was Bish. of Limoge in France, who liued in the yeare 50. of whom Baronius doth write. Likewiſe may be allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the fiue liturgies or Maſſes of the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">In Mart. 30. Iun. Proclus de Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</note> The firſt of S. Peter, in defence of which, Willaim Lindane a learned Catholike writeth an Apologie. The ſecond of S <hi>Iames</hi> the greater, alleaged by S. Proclus Patriarch of Conſtantinople, who liued in the yeare 460, The third of S. <hi>Iames</hi> the leſſer, alleaged by the fore ſaid proclus, wherof mention is made likewiſe in the Councell of Trull. in the yeare 680. The fourth, the liturgie of S. Mathew, which the Aethiopians do vſe, and is called in their language <hi>Corbon,</hi> that is <hi>Miſſah</hi> in Hebrew, and in Latin <hi>Oblatio;</hi> of this Liturgy or terme of Maſſe writeth Genebrard.<note place="margin">Gen. in finc pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia ſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi. Vbi ſup.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The fift is that of <hi>S. Mark</hi> vſed long time in
<hi>Alexandria,</hi> of this likewiſe writeth <hi>Genebrard.</hi> Of theſe
<hi>Liturgies</hi> writeth <hi>Coccius,</hi> lib. de <hi>Euchar.</hi> art. 1.4. likewiſe mention is made of them, in the booke cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Bibliotheca Patrum</hi> in the 6. Tom. of the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 1589.</p>
            <p>But leaſt we become tedious to your graue At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, we will bring onely the Teſtimonies of ſome holy Fathers, who liued in the moſt flouris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hing <pb n="18" facs="tcp:18148:15"/> eſtate of Chriſts Church, who be moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended of our Aduerſaries.</p>
            <p>The firſt of or <hi>VVitneſſes</hi> shalbe <hi>S. Denis Areopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gite</hi> diſciple of <hi>S. Paul,</hi> of whom there is mention made in the actes of the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Act. 17 14.</note> who liued in the yeare 90. of whom <hi>Sutcliffe</hi> the Proteſtant writer ſaith:<note place="margin">de presb cap. 13. pag. 91 Orm. in his pictu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re of a Puritan. pa. 1605. Eccl. hiſt. cap. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Dionyſius antiquitatis optimus ſanè teſtis, videtur enim eſſe antiquiſsimus</hi> This
<hi>S. Denis</hi> then, who (as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Oliuier Ormerod</hi> a learned Proteſtant writeth) liued in the Apoſtles times; in his Eccleſiaſticall Hierarchie ſetteth downe the moſt of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, that the Catholike Church vſeth in celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Maſſe: viz the prayers the burning of Frankincenſe about the Altar, the ſinging of Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, parcells of ſcripture which be read, the washing of handes, the giuing of the Pax, the Eleuation of the holy Hoſte, the Adoration of theſame, the Comunion &amp; receauing of the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, yea, he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, that no ſooner the B. Sacrament is on the Altar, but there be preſent troopes of Saints, This ancient Father in all his books maketh, ſo much for vs, both in this &amp; all other pointes of our Catholike Faith, and againſt our Aduerſaries, that Caluine,<note place="margin">Lib 1. ca 1 §. 4 C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1. li. 2 c 10 col
637.</note> &amp; the Century writers haue no other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, but to call in queſtion the bookes of <hi>S. Denis,</hi> albeit moſt vniuſtly, preferring the ſaying and falſe opinion of <hi>Eraſmus</hi> &amp;
<hi>Laurentius Valla</hi> (both Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s) before the authority of an infinite number <pb n="19" facs="tcp:18148:15"/> of ancient Doctors. <hi>Origen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Orig. hom. 2. indiuerſ ante med. Athanaſ in Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pera <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ionyſii Chryſ. epiſt. ad Carolu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Caluum gric. hom. 34 Fulk. in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fut. of Purgat. pag 353. Coup in his dict. at the wo d Diony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius. pag.
105.</note> who liued in the yeare 230. in one of his Homilies alleadging a paſſage of <hi>S. Denis</hi> his <hi>Caelestiall Hierarchy,</hi> termeth him Great <hi>S. Deniſe</hi> Areopagite, <hi>S. Athanaſius,</hi> who liued in the yeare 319 that Great Diuine. <hi>S. Chryſoſtome,</hi> who liued in the yeare 390 that Caeleſtiall birde. <hi>S. Gregor.</hi> the Great, who liued in the yeare 590. Calleth him ancient &amp; venerable Father. And not only are his bookes acknowledged by the ancient Fathers, but euen by our late Proteſtante writers, as by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Fulk, Hermanus, <hi>D. Bridges</hi> Lord Bishop of Oxford, who did thinke him to haue beene before <hi>S. Baſils</hi> dayes, who liued in the yeare 370. by M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Cooper late Bishop of wincheſter; by M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Oliuier Ormrod in his picture of a puritane in proofe of the Croſſe made in Baptiſme; And by the Archbishop of Canterb, in his anſwere to an admonition. And this concerning our firſt witnes.</p>
            <p>The ſecond of our <hi>VVitneſſes</hi> is <hi>S. Ignatius, Scholler</hi> vnto <hi>S. Iohn</hi> the Euangeliſt, who liued in the yeare
100. writeth thus in his vndoubted Epiſtle ad <hi>Smyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ad <hi>Smyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſes.</hi>
               </note> that the Bishop is as highe Prieſt in reſpecte of his Prieſthood, affirming further, that in the Church nothing is greater then the Bishop who ſacrificeth vnto God for the ſafety of the whole world, becauſe it is (ſaith he) not lawfull without a Bishop to offer immaculate Sacrifice,<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> to celebrate <pb n="20" facs="tcp:18148:16"/> the maſſe, &amp;c. This ſaying of <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, &amp; not gainſaid by the late Bishop of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terb. M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Whitgift in his Def. pag. 408. For fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proofe of this and like ſayings of <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> ſee <hi>S. Hierom lib. de viris illuſtribus. ibidem:</hi> it is not lawfull without a Bishop to offer Sacrifice, or to ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate maſſe.</p>
            <p>The third <hi>VVitneſſe</hi> is <hi>S. Irenaeus Scoller</hi> to <hi>S. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licarpus,</hi> who was Diſciple to <hi>S. Iohn Euangeliſt,</hi> and liued in the yeare 170, who ſome times was Bishop of Lyons in France;<note place="margin">Lib. 4. aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ.</note> This
<hi>Irenaeus</hi> affirmeth, that, beſides the ſpirituall Prieſtly Order of all the Iuſt, another peculiar Prieſthood of the Apoſtles, who are in reſpect therof to attend dailye vpon God &amp; the Altar.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Dialog. cum Tryph.</note>The fourth
<hi>VVitneſſe</hi> is <hi>Iuſtinus Mart.</hi> who liued in the yeare 130. he affirmeth, that the ſacrifice of the Euchariſt is by the Inſtitution of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp; that it is celebrated throughout all the world by the Chriſtians,<note place="margin">Euſeb. li. 4 c. 17 Hier. in catalog.</note> and that by the Prieſts only, his bookes and workes are reported by <hi>Euſebius</hi> and <hi>S. Hierom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Origen. hom 21. in Num.</note>The fift
<hi>VVitneſſe</hi> is <hi>Origen,</hi> who liued the yeare 230. In his 21 homily on the booke of Numeri, (the which homilies he did write before his falling into error,) doth Iudge, that it appertaineth only to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that liue chaſt continually, to offer ſacrifice,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:18148:16"/>The ſixt <hi>VVitneſſe</hi> is <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. 63 ad Caecil.</note> who liued in the yeare 240. in his Epiſtle <hi>ad Caecilium</hi> ſaith thus: If <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> our Sauiour &amp; God, be himſelf cheif Prieſt of his Father, and the firſt who did offer vp himſelf as a ſacrifice to God the Father, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded vs to doe the ſame in commemoration of him; Truely it followeth, that the Prieſt, who imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates that, which Chriſt did doe, is in the place of Chriſt, and doth offer vp to God the Father a true, and full ſacrifice, whenſoeuer he beginneth to offer according to that manner, as was offered by <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> this <hi>S. Cyprian;</hi> for the which wordes the Century writers do reproue and reiect him.</p>
            <p>The ſeuenth <hi>VVitneſſe</hi> is <hi>S. Baſil,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Liturg. Eccleſ. Cappad. apud Cocc. li. de Euch.</note> who profeſſed a monaſticall life, and liued in the yeare 370. He ſetteth downe the ceremonies &amp; forme of the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the maſſe, which were obſerued within his dioceſſe, he being then Bishop of <hi>Caeſarea in Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padocia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 8. <hi>VVitneſſe</hi> is <hi>S Iohn Chryſoſtome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib de Sacerd.</note> who liued in the yeare 390. in his booke <hi>de Sacerdotio.</hi> ſpeaking of the conſecration of the hoſt in the ſacrifice of the maſſe ſaith thus. The wordes are pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced by the Prieſt, and are conſecrated by the grace,<note place="margin">Chryſ. orat. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes qd. vnus eſt Deus.</note> &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of God. The booke, which he maketh of Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, is a ſufficient proofe of his opinion, in this and other points of our Catholike Religion, in <pb n="22" facs="tcp:18148:17"/> the which book he affirmeth, that in Britanie there were <hi>Altaria Chriſto dedicata.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 9 <hi>VVitneſſe</hi> is <hi>Tertullian</hi> one of the Latine Churche, who liued in the yeare 220. whoſe autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie is reuerenced, not only by the Ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,<note place="margin">In his picture of a Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. pa 3</note> but likewiſe by our aduerſaryes. Ormerod a Proteſtant writer doth alledge <hi>Tertullian</hi> his opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſigne of the croſſe Baptiſme againſt his Puritane Brethren. This <hi>Tertullian</hi> amongſt the other traditions of the Catholike Churche,<note place="margin">Lib. de Coron. milit cap. 3.</note> reports of the ſaying of maſſe, or oblation at the end of the yeare for the Soules departed The which ſentence is acknowledged by M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Fulk to be of <hi>Tertullian.</hi> And in his booke <hi>de cultu faeminarum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In his confut. of purg pag. 362</note> he ſaith, that a woman should not goe abrode, vnleſſe it be to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t the ſicke, heare the ſermon, or aſsiſte in the Churche at maſſe.</p>
            <p>The Ninth <hi>VVitneſſe</hi> is <hi>S. Ambroſe,</hi> who liued in the yeare 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0. and whome the Century-writers do reiect,<note place="margin">Lib 4 cap 4 col. 295</note> for his to much writing in fauor of the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the maſſe &amp; Catholike Prieſthood. Amongſt other of his ſayings he confeſſed of himſelf, that tumult being riſen in the aſſembly where he was,<note place="margin">Ambro. lib. 5 Epiſt.
3</note> yet he was not forgetfull of his office, but did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne the maſſe.</p>
            <p>The eleuenth of our <hi>VVitneſſes</hi> is <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> Scoller to <hi>S. Ambroſe,</hi> he died in the yeare 430. he is <pb n="23" facs="tcp:18148:17"/> plentifull in this &amp; other points of Catholike do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, euen in the Iudgment of our Aduerſaryes,<note place="margin">Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us in his Exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. part. 3. pag. 3.</note> he named the word maſſe in one of his Sermons ſaying, <hi>lett no man</hi> be abſent from the maſſe on ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day. And againe he named the word maſſe in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sermon ſaying, theſe words, which shalbe read at the maſſe, and elſe where.<note place="margin">Auguſt. ſerm. 51 de tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore. Ser. 91. de tem. Ser. 337.</note> Vniuſtly therefore do our aduerſaryes obiect againſt vs, ſaying that <hi>S. Auguſt.</hi> did neuer name the word maſſe. And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>S. Auſtins</hi> time the 2. Councell of Carthage in the 3. chap and the Mileuitan Councell cap. 12. doth name the word maſſe. And before
<hi>S. Austin, S. Ambroſe,</hi> who liued anno 390. in his 5. book of Epiſtles, Epiſt 33 <hi>S. Damaſus</hi> Pope, who liued about the yeare.
384. in his book of the liues of the Popes. And <hi>S. Macharius,</hi> who liued about anno 319. in his decret. de conſecrat. named the word maſſe.
<hi>S. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bianus</hi> Pope in one of his Decrees, who liued about the yeare
242. <hi>S. Sother</hi> Pope &amp; Martyr, who liued about the yeare 171. in one of his Decrees which are extant Tom. Concil. <hi>S. Pius</hi> Pope Anno
147<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in one of his Decrees. <hi>S. Higinus</hi> Pope &amp; Martyr Anno
144. in his Decree as Ino. lib. 2. teſtifieth. <hi>S. Alexander</hi> Pope &amp; Martyr Anno 121. Epiſt. 1 ad omnes Orthodoxos, which is to be ſeene in the Councell of Tribury cap. 19. <hi>S. Clement</hi> third Pope after <hi>S. Peter</hi> Epiſt. 3. Anno 111. <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> the <pb n="24" facs="tcp:18148:18"/> Apoſtles Scoller. Epiſt. ad Smyrnenſes. All which holy men did name the word Maſſe properly, and in that ſame ſenſe, that the Catholikes at this day do vſe. Yet for all this forſooth our Aduerſaryes would make the world belieue, that the word Maſſe, is a word newly inuented, &amp; not found in the primitiue Churche. But they deale with vs in this, as in many other things, which muſt proceed either of malice, or of groſſe ignorance.</p>
            <p>The twelfe of our <hi>VVitneſſes</hi> is <hi>S. Hierome,</hi> who liued in the ſame time that <hi>S. Auſtin,</hi> did. A<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 430. He is generally holden of our Aduerſaries to be for the Catholike Religion in this,<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Heliod.</note> &amp; other points: He did reuerence &amp; reſpect holy Prieſthood very much, ſaying: God forbid I should ſpeake amiſſe of them, who ſucceding, doe conſecrate with their mouth the body,<note place="margin">Cyrillus Catech Cyrillus Hieroſ. catech. 12. Gregor N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſen orat. in muliere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peccat. Ep ph. Haereſ.
73.</note> &amp; blood of Ieſus Chriſt. To theſe <hi>VVitneſſes</hi> wee might adde infinite more, if it were not tedious to your honors. As <hi>S. Cyrill</hi> of Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria contemporaneo to <hi>S. Hieron. S, Cyrillus Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſolymitanus</hi> Anno 320. <hi>S. Gregory of Nyſsen. Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, Athanaſius</hi> Anno 319. <hi>Optatus</hi> Anno 350. lib. 6. aduerſus Haereſ. <hi>Athan.</hi> quaeſt. 34.</p>
            <p>Right honorable, Reuerend, Graue, and Learned, theſe be our
<hi>VVitneſſes</hi> who did direct our fore ſaid <hi>Iury</hi> in their
<hi>Verdict:</hi> at whom our Aduerſaries can take no exception iuſtly, ſeing they were men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different <pb n="25" facs="tcp:18148:18"/> and not angrie neither at our Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries not at vs; and who be much eſteemed of, by the more aduiſed and ſober Proteſtants,<note place="margin">chemint exam. Concil. Trid. part. 1, pag. 74.</note> who (to vſe their owne words) doubt not, but that the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Churche re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaued from the Apoſtles, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall men, not only the text of Scripture, but alſo the right and natiue ſenſe therof; And that we are greatly confirmed,<note place="margin">Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemi pag. 400</note> in the true &amp; ſound ſenſe of Scripture, by teſtimonies of the ancient Fathers; And that they are the true and beſt Maſters of poſteritie, going before &amp; leading vs the way: and as M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Bancroft late Bishop of Canterb, ſaith:<note place="margin">Bancr. ſurvey. pag. 379.</note> for M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Caluin and M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Beza I doe thinke of them as their writings deſerue, but yet I thinke better of the ancient Fathers, I muſt confeſſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>SECTION. IIII.</hi> The Confeſsion of twelue of the learnedeſt of the Aduerſarie parties.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIRDLY if the parties owne Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion be of force (as doubtles in all reaſon it is no leſſe then Conuincing) your Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes shall heare the graueſt of your Aduerſaryes confirme by their ouwne Confeſsion, this point of doctrine for vs.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:18148:19"/>1. Caluine our Aduerſaries prime man ſpeaking of <hi>Irenaeus, Tertullian, Origen, Auguſt:</hi> and others, how highly they eſteemed the Church of Rome,<note place="margin">Inſt lib 4 cap
2. §. 2.</note> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Succeſsion of the Romane Bishops, anſwereth &amp; giueth his like reaſon there of ſaying: Conſidering it was a matter out of all doubt, that from the beginning euen vntill that time (viz till <hi>S. Auſtins</hi> time) nothing was changed in doctrine, the holy doctors tooke in argument that which was ſufficient for the ouerthrowing of all new er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors; viz, that they viz: the heretikes oppugned the doctrin, which euen from the very Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues had beene inuiolably and with one conſent retained Againe in his booke of <hi>Inſtitutions</hi> ſet forth in French he ſaith expreſly,<note place="margin">Inſtit in French printed at Gena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua anno 1561.</note> that it was a thing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious &amp; without doubt, that after the Apoſtles age vntill thoſe times viz: (<hi>S. August</hi> his time) no change was made in doctrine, neither at Rome nor at other cittyes. Now ſeeing aluine affirmeth that without all doubt there was no change of doctrine in the Church of Rome, from the beginning (that is from the Apoſtles times) vntill <hi>S. Aug.</hi> his time, which was for 400. and odd yeares after Chriſt, it muſt follow in Caluins opinion, that the doctrine we haue heretofore alleaged, by the teſtimony of our Iury (viz the Councells) and witneſſes (viz the Fathers) they being all both Iury and witneſſes <pb n="27" facs="tcp:18148:19"/> within the ſaid firſt 400. and od yeares; is pure do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, &amp; inuiolably &amp; with one conſent retained, from the very Apoſtles themſelues.</p>
            <p n="2">2. BEZA Scoller to Caluin,<note place="margin">Confeſſ. Gen ca. 7. Sect. 12.</note> ſaith that <hi>Leo who was Pope Anno Domini</hi>
440. did clearly breath forth, the arrogancie of the Antichriſtian Romane Sea. Now ſeing <hi>S. Sixtus</hi> 3. who was predeceſſor to this
<hi>Leo,</hi> did confirme the Canons of the generall Councell of Epheſus, which proueth the maſſe to be a Sacrifice,<note place="margin">vt ſupra</note> &amp; that vnbloody which is offered daylie in the Church, therefore I ſay it followeth, according to Beza his opinion, that this Pope
<hi>Sixtus</hi> did breath forth no arroganty nor Antichriſtan doctrine, ſeing he was before <hi>Leo,</hi> who was the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt according to Bezas ſaying, &amp; conſequently the maſſe not to be Antichriſtian doctrine, but Chriſtian &amp; true doctrine.</p>
            <p n="3">3. MELANCTHON ſaith:<note place="margin">In locis poſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</note> 
               <hi>Zozimus</hi> (who was Pope Anno 420) was the firſt Antichriſt; &amp; that ſince there was neuer any true Bishop of Rome. Now if <hi>Zozimus</hi> was the firſt Antichriſt &amp; falſe Bishop, it followeth that <hi>Innocentius</hi> (who allowed of abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from ſinnes by a prieſt,<note place="margin">Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Epiſt. 1. Vecen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca 7.</note> who was predeceſſor to <hi>Zozimus</hi>) was no Antichriſt, but a good Chriſtian and true Bishop, &amp; did teach Chriſtian and true doctrine, And not only he, but alſo all the reſt of the Bishops of the Romane Sea, who were before <pb n="28" facs="tcp:18148:20"/> 
               <hi>Innocentius</hi> the firſt (the number of which amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to 41.) were true Bishops &amp; did teach true do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, And conſequently Catholike Prieſthood teached, allowed and practiſed by them, is true and Chriſtian doctrine, euen according to Melancthon his opinion.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">Lib. de Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chr ſto contra Sand pag.
35.</note>4 MR. WHITAKER a learned Aduerſary, being vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the Catholike writer <hi>D. Sanders,</hi> who affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that the Catholike &amp; Romane Church was not cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged during the firſt 600. yeares after Chriſt; acknowledged the ſame to be true ſaying, during all that time the Church was pure &amp; florishing, and inuiolably taught and defended the Faith deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from the Apoſtles. Now according to this Aduerſaryes Confeſsion, it followeth that Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Prieſthood, &amp; other points of doctrine, taught by thoſe Ancient Fathers, brought as witneſſes he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retofore in defence of our cauſe, muſt be pure doctrine, &amp; inuiolably deliuered from the Apoſtles. 5.<note place="margin">In his Conf. of purgat. pag. 373</note> MR. FVLK doth graunt that the cauſe why
<hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus, Cyprian. Tertull. Optatus, and Vincentius Lyrinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, Hierom, &amp; Auguſtine</hi> did name the Church of Rome, was becauſe the Church of Rome at that time, as it was founded by the Apoſtles, ſo it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in the doctrine of the Apoſtles. Now ſeing thoſe very ſame Fathers, are alleaged by vs as Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, in defence of our cauſe, it followeth, by M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:18148:20"/> Fulkes owne Confeſsion; that our doctrine in this point, is the doctrine of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p n="6">6. MR. NAPPER (that renouned Proteſtant) auou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to his Maieſtie that Pope <hi>Siluester</hi> who liued about Anno 313.<note place="margin">Vppon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelat. p. 66. 68.</note> was the Antichriſt but ſeing all theſe Popes, who were before Pope <hi>Silueſter</hi> his time (he being but the thirty fourth Pope) were all Prieſts and practiſed ther Prieſthood by ſaying of maſſe, &amp;c did practiſe or teach no Antichriſtian doctrine, ſeing (as M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Napper affirmeth) the Antichriſt was not as yet come, but Chriſtian &amp; holſome doctrine was taught by them, and conſequently a Maſsing Prieſt, to be no new or Antichriſtian doctrine.</p>
            <p n="7">7. MR. GIFFORD in his demonſtrations that Browniſts are Donatiſts, &amp;c. ſaith:<note place="margin">pag. 38.</note> 
               <hi>To offer oblation</hi> for the dead, was generall in the Church, long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the dayes of <hi>S. Auſtin,</hi> as appeareth in <hi>Cyprian</hi> &amp;
<hi>Tertullian.</hi> Now ſeing that <hi>Cyprian</hi> &amp;
<hi>Tertullian</hi> liued within 240. yeares after Chriſt, all the which time yea euen to <hi>S. Auſtins</hi> time, the Churche did florish, and did maintanie the doctrine of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles heretofore confeſſed; It muſt follow that Oblation for the dead was good, and faithfull do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, ſeing it was generally holden, &amp; maintained by the Church.<note place="margin">Of the Church li. 3 c 29 pa. 138.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. MR. FIELD reporting the errors of <hi>Aerius</hi> the heretike ſaith: <hi>Aerius</hi> condemned the cuſtome of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18148:21"/> the Church, in naming the dead at the Altar, and offering the ſacrifice of the Euchariſt, that is, of thankeſgeuing for them: hee diſliked of ſett Faſtes, and would not admitt any difference betweene a Bishop &amp; a Presbyter, &amp;c. he was iuſtly condemned thus hee. Now ſeing that M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Field ſaith, that Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius was iuſtly condemned, for not allowing the mention of the dead, made at the Altar, &amp; the offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſacrifice of the Altar, &amp;c it followeth, that M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Field allowes of mention to be made for the dead at an Altar, and of a ſacrifice, (albeit he call this ſacrifice of the Euchariſt a Thankſgiuing, but I muſt confeſſe moſt improperly,) but none of thoſe be practiſed this day in the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, all Altars being deſtroyed, &amp; the word
<hi>(Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice)</hi> banished; And conſequently in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Field his opinion, mentioning the dead at the Altar, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering ſacrifice is ſound doctrine, &amp; the contrary is error, iuſtly condemned by the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pag 3.</note>MR. GODWIN<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in his Catalogue of the Bishops of England, ſpeaking of <hi>S. Gregory</hi> the great Bishop of Rome, ſaith: That bleſſed and holy Father <hi>S. Gregory</hi> was the occaſion of replanting the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith in our countrey: But none of our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries can denie, but <hi>S. Gregory</hi> did allow of maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Prieſts, yea he being one himſelf, and likewiſe of euery particular point of our now profeſſed Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike <pb n="31" facs="tcp:18148:21"/> Faith, As Altars, Veſtiments, Images, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lices, Croſſes, Candleſtikes, Cenſers, holy veſſels, holy water, the ſprinkling therof: with many other points, &amp; Ceremonies reported by the Proteſtant writer D. Humfrey in Ieſuitiſmi part. 2. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore according to M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Godwine it muſt follow,<note place="margin">Cap.
5. pag. 5.</note> that all theſe points, are points of Chriſtian do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, ſeing theſe be the points in which we En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glishmen were firſt inſtructed, by <hi>S. Augustine,</hi> ſent for that purpoſe into England, by <hi>S. Gregory</hi> the great Pope of Rome.</p>
            <p>MR. IEWEL,<note place="margin">Hooker. l. 2. ſect. 6 p.
112.</note> (whom M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Hooker in his Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Policij, termeth the worthieſt diuine, that chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome breed for ſome hundred yeares paſt,) in his reply to M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Harding pag. 246. ſaith: Aſwell <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> as alſo other godly Fathers, rightly yelded reuerence to the Sea of Rome, &amp;c. for the purity of Religion, which was there preſerued a long time without ſport: thus hee. But ſeing not only after, but likewiſe before <hi>S. Auſtins</hi> daies, the Church of Rome did allowe of maſsing Prieſts, &amp; other points of our now profeſſed Catholike Faith (as we haue shewed at lardge heretofore in our ſaid Iurye: Therfore according to M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Iewells ſaying, Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Prieſthood is a pure &amp; Chriſtian doctrine.</p>
            <p>MR. RIDLEY ſaith in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Fox Actes and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents:<note place="margin">pa. 1359.</note> the Patriarch of Rome (ſo he termeth the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18148:22"/> Pope) in the Apoſtles times and long after, was a great maintainer and ſetter forth of Chriſts glory, in the which aboue all other countreyes, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions was preached the true Goſpell, the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts were moſt duely adminiſtred, &amp;c: After the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pors became Chriſtians (ſaith he) the Goſpell there florished moſt: But all the Popes who were in the firſt, ſecond, and third hundred yeares, did allow of Catholike Prieſthood, Witneſſe of this is <hi>S. Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> Pope, who was third Pope after <hi>S. Peter,</hi> and liued about the yeare 102 who ſaith,<note place="margin">Ep. 3.</note> thus in one of his Epiſtles: Let noe Prieſt ſay maſſe in his Parish, without the licence of his Bishop. And by ſaying of Maſſe, the Euchariſt was giuen and receiued o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the people, as is witneſſed by <hi>S. Dionyſe, S. Ignatius,</hi> &amp; <hi>S. Marcellus</hi> who liued in the ſecond Age, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath beene shewed: After <hi>S. Clement</hi> ſucceeded <hi>S. Anaclete,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anacle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Ep. 1</note> in the yeare 03 who commaunded that maſſe should be celebrated, only in holy places After him <hi>S, Alexander</hi> who died for the Faith in the yeare 131.<note place="margin">Baron. in mart. 3 May.</note> he did confirme the Apoſtolike con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, of mingling wine with water in the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the maſſe.<note place="margin">In de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretis Sixti Papae.</note> After him was
<hi>S. Sixtus Romanus,</hi> in the yeare 142. who commaunded, that the ſacred veſſels vſed at maſſe, &amp; at other times should not be handled, nor touched by any man, but by the who were in holy Orders. After him was
<hi>S, Feleſphor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:18148:22"/> who had binan anchorite in Greece, he died in the yeare 154. he ordained, that the maſſe should be celebrated in the night in Chriſtmaſſe euen, &amp;c. After him ſucceeded <hi>S. Pius</hi> an Italian, who died in the yeare 167. in one of his Epiſtles to <hi>Iuſtus</hi> Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hop of Vienna he ſaith:<note place="margin">Tom. 1. Biblio SS. Patru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> we do celebrate the maſſe in the Churche of <hi>Euprepia, &amp;c.</hi> After him, (or as ſome ſay, before him) ſucceeded <hi>S. Anicet,</hi> who died in the yeare 175. he would that the Prieſt should beare a shauen crowne;<note place="margin">Anacle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Ep. ad Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los.</note> his decrees are extant Tom. 1. Concil. After him ſucceeded <hi>Soter,</hi> and died 179. who commaunded, that none should celebrate maſſe without one to help him. And ſo ſucceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely one after another vntill <hi>S. Silueſters</hi> time, who was Pope in the time of Conſtantine the great, the firſt Chriſtian Emperor, who was Chriſtened by the ſaid <hi>S. Silueſter.</hi> Theſe be the Bishops of Rome, (whom M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Ridley termeth Patriarkes) who did maintaine pure doctrine. All of them being before Conſtantine the firſt true Chriſtian Emperor. And as for that he ſaith, that in the firſt Chriſtian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors times the Goſpell did florish, it is moſt manifeſt that Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantine, who was Emperor in the yeare of our Lord 306. did allow of Monkes through out <hi>Syria, Paleſtina, Bithynia, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cent. cent. 4. col 2441.</note> did keepe in his company &amp; court Maſsing Prieſts, with all prouiſion to that effect, as <hi>Zozimus</hi> affirmeth; he <pb n="34" facs="tcp:18148:23"/> did attribut ſupremacie to the Bishop of Rome,<note place="margin">Zozim. hiſt. li. 1 cap. 8. Frig. in his pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ad Sereniſſ Regina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Aug.</note> as affirmeth <hi>Frigiuellaus Gauius</hi> a Proteſtant Writer: with other points of our Catholike doctrine, in whoſe time, the Churches doctrine was one and the ſame as it is at this day, concerning Freewill, iuſtification by workes, Confeſsion of ſinnes to a Prieſt, Inioined penance; Abſolution of ſuch as had confeſſed, giuen by impoſition of handes; Alſo with affirming penance to be the ſecond table after Shipwrack, vnwritten Traditions, inuocation of Saints, Purgatory, Altars conſecrated, with the ſigne of the Croſſe &amp; Chriſme, the reall preſence, &amp; Tranſubſtantation,<note place="margin">Cent. 4.</note> ſacrificing for the dead, and many other points which the <hi>Centuriſts</hi> of
<hi>Magde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> call errors, of that time, <hi>Now ſeeing that Maiſter Ridley ſaith, that the firſt Biſhops of Rome, &amp; the firſt Christian Emperors did ſet out Chriſts glory, and did admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter duely the Sacraments;</hi> It followeth, that in his opinion theſe points defended, and taught by the Churche in thoſe times, are no leſſe now pure &amp; true doctrine, and that the Euchariſt is duely ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred by maſsing Prieſts.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sect 6.</note>MR. HOOKER in his praeface to his bookes of <hi>Eccl. Policy</hi> ſaith: That wee are right ſure of this, that nature, Scripture, &amp; experience haue all taught the world to ſeek for the ending of contentions, by ſubmitting it ſelf vnto ſome Iudiciall and <pb n="35" facs="tcp:18148:23"/> definitiue ſentence, whervnto neither parties that contend, may vnder any pretence refuſe to ſtand. Now ſeing all Generall &amp; Prouinciall Councells, haue giuen their Iudiciall, &amp; definitiue ſentence concerning this point in fauor of vs Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes; And on the other ſide, ſeing neither M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Hooker, nor any Proteſtant can alleadge any gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councell or Prouinciall, or any Synodicall Conuenticle before this laſt. 100. yeares, to the contrary: It followeth, according to M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Hooker, that wee should allow of the Sacrifice of the Maſſe, ſeing Councclls in their Iudiciall, &amp; definitiue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces haue allowed of it. And much more becauſe he affirmeth moſt conſtantly in his bookes of <hi>Eccl. Pol.</hi> that the Church of Rome is to be reputed as a part, and limme of the Church,<note place="margin">Lib. 5. pag. 188.</note> and houſe of God.</p>
            <p>But becauſe I can not tell whether our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, Will allow what their followes did write or teache in the dayes of Queene Elizabeth, ſeing they defend, (as D. Doue a Proteſtant writer affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth perſwaſ. pag. 31.) they may often change, and doe (at leaſt) at the change of euery Prince. Theſe be his own woordes, <hi>VVhen the maſſe was firſt Put down, King Henry had his Engliſh Liturgie, that was iudged abſolute without exception But when Edward came to the Crowne, that was condemned, and an other put <pb n="36" facs="tcp:18148:24"/> in the place, which Peeter Martyr, and Bucer did approue as very conſonant to Gods woord. VVhen Queen Eliſabeth beganne her raigne, the former was iudged to be full of imperfections, and a new was diuiſed, and allowed by the conſent of the Clergie. But about the midle of her raigne, we grew weary of that book and great meanes haue beene wrought to abandon that, and eſtabliſh another, which, although it was not obtayned, yet we doe (at the leaſt at euery change of Prince,) change our book of common prayer, we be ſo wanton, that we know not what we would haue.</hi> Thus Doctor Doue. Therfore to giue our Aduerſaries all aduantages, you shall heare the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte of thoſe Proteſtant writers, who haue written ſince the beginning of his Maieſties raigne in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, and ſo much, and ſo incharitably againſt vs Catholikes, that for that cauſe one of their owne number, (Ormer pict. Pap. in poſtſcript.) adiudgeth many of their bookes to the fire, and their Authors worthie of death.</p>
            <p>MR. MIDLETON Papiſtomaſt. pag. 137. 138. graunteth with <hi>S. Chryſoſt. S. Aug. S. Epiphan. That Sacrifice, and Prayer for the dead was an Apostolicall Tradition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>D SVTCLIFFE againſt the three Conuerſ. pag. 791. ſaith:
<hi>Chriſtes true Church is a diligent, and wary keeper of doctrines committed to her, and changeth nothing at any time, diminiſheth nothing, addeth nothing ſuperflius, <pb n="37" facs="tcp:18148:24"/> looſeth not her owne, nor vſurpeth things belonging to others.</hi> But ſeing. D. SVTCLIFFE can not deny, but the church of Rome was once Chryſts true church, therfore it followeth, according to D. Sutcliffe opinion, that the church of Rome muſt needes haue diligently, and warely kept the doctrine of ſuch a maine, and eſſentiall point of her cheife function, as is the Sacrifice of the Maſſe, nor chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging nor adding any thing ſuperfluous thervnto.</p>
            <p>MR. WILLET antilog, pag 144. aſſureth you, that diuerſe of the Romane Church, not only of the ignorant, but of the Learned, be ſaued and Saintes in heauen. His wordes be theſe. <hi>It is not denied, by any Proteſtant, but many renowned Kinges &amp; Queenes, (who might not plead ignorance of the Romane Faith) are ſaintes in heauen.</hi> And ſpeaking of his maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Mother, he attributeth ſuch holineſſe, and truth to her Religion and her, that it preuailed with God, not only for her ſelf, but her ſonne our ſoueraigne alſo, his wordes be. Willet antilog Engl. praef. to the K. <hi>The child of ſuch Prayers, and teares, cannot poſsibly fall away.</hi> Now if to aſsiſt at the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the Maſſe, is to committ idolatry, (as our aduerſaries would haue it,) M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Willet could neuer haue accounted theſe Kinges and Queenes, to be ſaintes in heauen, whoſe cheiffe and dayly exercice of deuotion was to aſsiſt therat.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:18148:25"/>D. Couell writeth of the Churche in theſe woordes in his def. of M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Hooker pag. 30 art. 4. <hi>That, which by her Eccleſiasticall authoritie ſhe ſhall probably think, and define to be true or good, moſt in congruity of reaſon ouer rule all other inferior iudgments, whatſoeuer; &amp; to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that out of a ſingularitie of their owne, aske vs, why we thus hang our iudgments on the Churches ſleeue, we anſwere with Salomon. Two are better then one, for when in matters of leſſe moment, it was neuer thought ſafe, to neglect the iudgment of many, and hasſly to follow the fancy and opinion of ſome fewe.</hi> Now, but that the Church of Rome hath had the definition of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councells, and conſent of Fathers in behalf of Catholike <hi>Prieſthood</hi> and other pointes of Religion contradicted this day, neither D. Couel, nor any man euer douted, &amp; hence it is, that D Couel (vbi ſupra pag. 73.) concludeth thus.
<hi>It is ſtrange for any man to deny them of the Church of Rome to be of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>D. Murton part. 2. apol. pag. 340. lib. 4. cap. 18 auoucheth confide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, that <hi>a generall Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell is higheſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> iudge;</hi> ſo doth the Bishop of Wincheſter, (B. Bilſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſuruey pag. 85.) and others; but all men know, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Proteſtants not to be able to produce any genera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Councell conſiſting of meere Proteſtantes, as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Proteſtant Relator of Religion. (Relat. of Relig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cap. 47.) ingeniouſly confeſſeth, and let it ſuffiſe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:18148:25"/> Catholikes to bring the late generall Councell of Trent, at the which Proteſtants Religion was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatim condemned as hereſie by ſix Cardinals, foure Legates, three Patriarches, two and thirtie Archbishops, 228. Bishops, and 4. Abbots. And ſo D. Morton muſt acknowledge the higheſt iudge to be for vs.</p>
            <p>D. Doue pleading for an vnion betwixt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes and Proteſtantes, ſpeaking in fauour of the Church of Rome, ſaith. <hi>No Church can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and adiudged hereticall by any priuate cenſure, but it muſt be publicke by a generall Councell.</hi> (D. Doue perſuaſ. pag.
14.) and pag 27. 28, he ſaith, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Catholikes definition of a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there be as many as they teach, and this shall not breed any ſuch iarre betwene vs, that therfore we should refuſe to communicate togeather, and tranſubſtantation it ſelfe shall be no bar. The Bishop of Wincheſter in his ſuruey, (B. Bilſons ſuruey pag. 85.) writeth thus.
<hi>The ancient conſent of Godly Fathers, is with great care to be ſcearched, and followed of vs, cheifly in the rule of faith.</hi> Now ſeing the ancient Fathers make for vs in this point, as hath thertofore beene shewed, it followeth the B. of Wincheſter muſt allow of this point in controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, ſeing it is there doctrine</p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Parkes againſt Limbom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtix pag. 86. <pb n="40" facs="tcp:18148:26"/> citeth, and approueth the Councell of Lateran, as a rule of Faith, but that this Councell alloweth of tranſubſtantation, Can. 1. of Confeſsion to a Prieſt, Can. 21. Celebrating of Maſſe, Can. 58. of Reliques, can 62. may eaſely be ſeen by any man, who will but read this Councell.</p>
            <p>D, Downam lib. 2. Antichriſt. pag. 165. graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth with S. Aug. and Victor Vticenſis, <hi>that, to adheare to the Church of Rome, was a marcke of a true Catholike in thoſe times.</hi> But what the Church of Rome held in thoſe dayes concerning Catholike Prieſthood, and other pointes of controuerſie, it may be ſeen by that, which hath beene heretofore ſaid.</p>
            <p>But not to ſeeme tedious to your wiſdomes, I will conclude this ſection with the reporte, which one of our aduerſaries the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues maketh of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, and of their Religion, Relation of the ſtat. of Relig. cap 48. the Authors wordes be; <hi>There are among them, (vndoubtedly) in great multitude, men ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, Learned, fraught with the loue of God, and the truth aboue all thinges, men of memorable integritie of harte an affections, (cap</hi> 6.) <hi>in their Sermons much matter, both of Faith and piety is eloquently deliuered by men of wonderfull zeale and ſpirit, &amp;c. (Ibidem.) The outward ſtate and glorie of their ſeruice doth ingender, quicken, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and nourriſhe the inward reuerence, reſpect, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:18148:26"/> deuotion, which is dve vnto Soueraigne Maieſtie, &amp; power (cap.</hi> 9.) <hi>there deedes of charitie are exceeding, (cap.</hi>
48.) <hi>we find amongst them excellent order of gouerment, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular helpes for increaſe of godlines, and deuotion, for the profiting of vertue.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>SECTION V.</hi> OF PRIORITIE of poſſeſsion.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT wiſe and Learned Iudges, we are not ignorant, but that Prioritie of Poſſeſsion amongſt you receaueth this fauour in your lawe, that to the party diſſeiſed of ſuch his poſſeſsion you afford ſpeciall remedy by Writt of Aſsiſe, allowing him alſo the benefitt of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall claime, to preuent diſcent vpon the other parties dying ſeyſed. Therefore we require your graue conſiderations concerning this pointe of Prioritie of Poſſeſsion, how it maketh for vs, and againſt our aduerſaries, euen they being Iudges.</p>
            <p>The holy Fathers doubt not vpon this ground of Prioritie of Poſſeſsion to vrge the Succeſsion of the Romane Bishops, as a ſtrong &amp; vnanſwerable argument againſt the Heretikes of thoſe times. So
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:18148:27"/> 
               <hi>Irenaeus</hi> againſt the Heretikes of his time; you ought (ſaith he) to obey thoſe,<note place="margin">Irenaeus lib. 3. adu hae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſes. cap. 3.</note> who haue their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion from the Apoſtles, &amp;c So <hi>Tertull. lib. de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript. aduerſus haereſ.</hi> let haeretikes ſet forth the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnig of their Churches, let them recount the order of their ſucceeding Bishops, if they can. And after ſetting downe in ranke the Bishops of Rome from S. <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Eleutherius,</hi> he ſaith: <hi>Confingant tale quid Haeretici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c.</hi> let Heretikes bring forth any ſuch thing,<note place="margin">S. Hier. vnic. Lyr.</note> &amp;c. So
<hi>S. Hierom in Apol.</hi> 1. <hi>adu. Ruffinum.</hi> So <hi>Vincentius Lyrinenſis adu. Haereſes.</hi> Commendeth the Romane Church for maintayning alwayes, with ſo great force, ſtudy, and contention, <hi>(Suſceptae ſemel Religionis integritatem)</hi> the puritie of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which it firſt receaued. So did <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> againſt <hi>Manichaeus;</hi> theſe be his wordes:<note place="margin">Auguſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Ep. Manich cap. 4. Tom. 7.</note>
               <hi>Multa ſunt quae in Eccleſiae gremio me iuſtiſsime teuent, &amp;c.</hi> I am held in the beſome of the Church by the Succeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Prieſts, &amp; Bishops, that haue come downe euen from the firſt Seate of S. <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle to the preſent Bishop of Rome
<hi>Anastaſius,</hi> that holdeth the Seate at this day; thus he.<note place="margin">Reyn in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with M. Hart. pag. 443</note> The which ſaying of <hi>S. Aug.</hi> being vrged by a Catholike Writer M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>
               <hi>Hart</hi> againſt M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noldes;</hi> He maketh him aknowledge, that the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion of the Romane Bishops was a proofe of true Faith in the time of <hi>S. Auguſtine, Epiphan, Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatus, Tertullian,</hi> &amp;
<hi>Irenaeus.</hi> The like acknowledgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <pb n="43" facs="tcp:18148:27"/> or anſwere thereto is made by many other Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Proteſtants, as by M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>
               <hi>Ridley</hi> in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Fox</hi> his Acts &amp; Mon. pag. 1359. by M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>
               <hi>Iewell</hi> in his Reply to M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Harding.</hi> pag. 246. by Caluin in his Inſtit. li. 4. ca. 2. Now if Poſseſsion and Succeſsion of ſome hundred yeares were ſo eſteemed of by thoſe holy Fathers, yea euen by our aduerſaryes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, as a proofe of true Faith and Apoſtolicall doctrine; Shall not the Poſſeſsion with a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall, &amp; not interrupted Succeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of 239. Bishops, during a thouſand ſixe hundred and odde yeares, be of great force &amp; valew? and shall not ſuch a Prioritie of Poſſeſsion receaue fauour in your lawe? ſeing it is but the laſt day, and as yet within your owne appointed time of
<hi>Limitation,</hi> ſince we in this kingdome were thruſt out of our former rightfull, &amp; ſo long continued poſſeſsion, (all contrary to the Auncient lawes of Nations) condemned of crime, and tranſgreſsion in the matter of Religion, not ſo much as hauing our accuſers before vs, nor place to defend vs concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the crime.</p>
            <p>But our Aduerſaryes, beeing not able to denie this Succeſsion of Bishops in the Sea of Rome, for ſo doing it were to oppoſe themſelues againſt all writers, both ſacred, &amp; prophane; they Imagine
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:18148:28"/> a ſuppoſed change of Religion during the fore ſaid ſucceſsion.</p>
            <p>Pleaſeth it therefore your wiſedomes, we shew further demonſtration of her not change in this point mentioned in our application, neither in any Article of Faith, by manifeſt teſtimonie of our learned aduerſaries. It is generally confeſſed by our Aduerſaries, that our now profeſſed Cath. Faith concerning Cath. Prieſthood, &amp; likewiſe all other needfull points of Faith, profeſſed not only by the Catholiks of England, but of all Nations where the Cath. Faith is profeſſed, is one and the ſame, which hath beene taught, &amp; defended theſe laſt 1000. yeares, euen ſince our conuerſion from Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſme to the Chriſtian Faith by <hi>S. Auſtine</hi> the Monke, ſent by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> into England; that it was moſt vndoubtedly our now profeſſed Cath. Faith, it remaineth yet to this preſent day euident in two ſpeciall reſpects: As firſt by our eſtablished continuance in our Cath. Faith without any other noted, or known beginning thereof, or of any one part thereof from this preſent age, vp to the firſt time of our firſt conuerſion, for otherwiſe, could the English Cronographers of euery of thoſe meane ages make dalie mention of the other Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, &amp; changes, which happened in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome either in temporall, or Church affaires? could
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:18148:28"/> could they recite in particular the noted hereſies ariſing, (As the hereſies of Lollards, Wicklifiſts, &amp; the reſt, ariſing in England &amp; noted by the ancient Hiſtoriographers, &amp; by our late Writers, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Stow,</hi> Holinshead, Fox, and the Century-writers in the fifth chapter of very Ctntury,) of foundations of ſo many Bishops Seas, cathedrall Churches, colleges, Monaſteries, &amp;c. (as are noted by M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Harriſon in his deſcription of England,)<note place="margin">Cap. 2. pa. 140.</note> Togethr alſo with the alteration of our temporall lawes, and ſo many mutations in gouerment by <hi>Saxons, Danes, Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans;</hi> and otherwiſe the many battailes fought, the many rebellions attempted, the ſucceſsion of Kings, &amp; times of their deathes, the creation of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, the onerthrow of noble families; and be withall yet wholy ſilent in that ſo great change of Religion? M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Godwin</hi> in his catalogue of the Bishops of England, reporting diſtinctly the very names, &amp; ſucceſsion in ſo many ſeuerall Seas of our English Catholike Bishops, euen from this preſent age vp to the foreſaid <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> once Bishop of Canterbury, reporting likewiſe their actes good or euill; yett makes no mention of any change or innouation brought, or aſſented to by any one of theſe many Bishops, ſo much as but in any one point of our now profeſſed Catholike Faith. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reas, (on the contrary part) we are able to shew to <pb n="46" facs="tcp:18148:29"/> them the beginning, &amp; contradiction of the aduerſe doctrine, not only of theſe innouatouts here in England, as of Wicliffs &amp; Tindall, their old &amp; new Apoſtles; but likewiſe of all haereſies, Innouation, Contradiction with the time &amp; place thereof, euen ſince the Apoſtles times. Your wiſedomes therefore may diſcerne, that our now profeſſed Cath. doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, thus perpetuating it ſelfe by the hand of time with a current, &amp; not interrupted ſucceſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued euen from the Raigne of King Henry the 8. vp to the firſt time of our ſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſion, demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrateth it ſelfe moſt plainly therby, to be the ſame vndoubted Cath. Religion, whereto we English<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were firſt conuerted by <hi>S. Auſtin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly this point is made as yet much more certaine &amp; euident, in that ſundry of our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, yea the moſt learned amongſt them as D. <hi>Humfrey,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Humf. in Ieſuit. part 2. ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 5. p. 5</note> 
               <hi>Carion. l.</hi> 4. <hi>in Cron. p.</hi> 567.
<hi>Luke Oſiander in his Epit. hiſt. Eccl. cent.</hi> 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 289.
<hi>&amp;</hi> 290. <hi>the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury-writers of Magdeburch. Cent.</hi> 6.
<hi>cap.</hi> 10. <hi>col</hi> 148 &amp; others, do deſcribe the particulars of Religion, ſo then taught, &amp; profeſſed by <hi>S. Gregory</hi> &amp;
<hi>S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi> writing and affirming the ſaid particulars, to be Altars, Veſtiments, Images, Chalices, Croſſes, Candleſtickes, Cenſars, holy Veſſels, holy water, the ſprinkling thereof, Reliques, Tranſlation of Reliques, Dedicating of Churches to the bones, &amp;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18148:29"/> ashes of Saints, conſecrating of Altars, Chalices, &amp; Corporalls, conſecration of the Font of Baptiſme, Chriſme, &amp; Oyle, Conſecration of Churches with ſprinkling of holy water, Celebration of Maſſe, the Archbishops Pallatt ſolemne Maſſe-time, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Maſſe bookes, a burden, (as they terme it) of ceremonies, Free will, Merite, and Iuſtification by workes, Penance, Satisfaction, Purgatory, the Vnmarried life of Prieſts, publique inuocation of Saints, and their worship, the worshipping of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Exorciſmes, Pardons, Vowes, Monachiſme, Tranſubſtantatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Praier for the dead, the Romane Bishops claime, &amp; exerciſe of Iuriſdiction, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy ouer all Churches; and laſtly euen the whole Chaos of Popish ſuperſtition, (as theſe Proteſtant Writers blaſphemouſly terme it.) So farre the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid writers affirme theſe particulars to haue bene taught by the Churche of Rome, and in the which the English men were firſt inſtructed by <hi>S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi> ſent by
<hi>S. Gregory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Printed at Baſil. 1558.</note> as
<hi>Io. Bale in Act. Rom Pont. pag.</hi> 44. 45. 46. ſaith, that
<hi>Auguſtine</hi> was ſent from <hi>Gregory</hi> to ſeaſon the English Saxons with Popish faith.</p>
            <p>Euen here, (Right honorable &amp; wiſe) might we make our ſtand, and ſo preſume without all further proceeding humbly to offer vp to your graue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations; whether it were not a point of high
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18148:30"/> Iudgement, &amp; altogether vnworthy your mature &amp; learned iudgements, to condemne, reiect, and make penall, Catholike Prieſthood, and that faith ſo long continued, not only in England by En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Catholikes, but likewiſe throughout all Chriſtendome, whervnto we Englishmen were conuerted by <hi>S. Greg.</hi> one of thoſe Fathers, by whom Mr. Iewell, (a famous Proteſtant) in his pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blique Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Paules Croſſe deſired to be tried, which neuer the leſſe the bouldeſt aduerſary, (as I belieue) dare not performe.</p>
            <p>Neither did our now profeſſed Cath. Faith take its beginning in <hi>S. Gregories</hi> time, but reached vp euen to the Apoſtles times, which appeareth alſo by conferring our foreſaid confeſſed Religion, taught vs by <hi>S. Greg.</hi> and <hi>S. August</hi> with that pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Faith, whervnto the <hi>Brittains</hi> of <hi>VVales</hi> were conuerted in the Apoſtles times: For whereas our learned aduerſaries do affirme, that our neighbours the <hi>Britains</hi> of <hi>VVales</hi> receaued the faith of Chriſt by the preaching of the Apoſtles, and held that Faith at
<hi>Auſtins</hi> comming; ſo affirmeth Mr. Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in his
<hi>Britannia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 40</note> Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> in his deſcription of <hi>Britannie</hi> volum. 1. p. 23 Mr. Fulke his booke againſt <hi>Heskin Sanders,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag 561.</note>
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by <hi>Godwin</hi> in his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta. og. of Bishops pag. 1. Mr.
<hi>Foxe</hi> in his Acts and Mon. pag. 463. ſaith: The <hi>Britains</hi> after the <pb n="49" facs="tcp:18148:30"/> receauing of the Faith neuer forſooke it, for any manner of falſe preaching of others, nor for tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp;c. Againe Mr. <hi>Midleton</hi> in his <hi>Papiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſtix</hi> proueth by ancient Authors, that the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell was taught &amp; preached there by <hi>Simon Zelotes, Ioſeph of Arimathaea, S. Paul the Apoſtle.</hi> More ouer,<note place="margin">Beda hiſt 2. ca. 2. Holmiſt vol. 1. li. 1. ca. 21.</note> it is alſo recorded by the Proteſt. writers, that vpon conference betwixt
<hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> &amp; the British Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops then had at a place called in <hi>S. Bedes</hi> time, <hi>Austin-izet,</hi> of the which place maketh like men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>Holinſhead</hi> in his great Chronicle of the laſt edition. The greateſt difference then ſtood vpon betwene <hi>Auſtine</hi> and them, were expreſly, and only mentioned to be certaine tolerable differences: viz: Their diſſent from the vſe of the Romane Church in their Ceremonies, or miniſtring of Baptiſme, &amp; keeping of Eaſter. <hi>Beda</hi> in his hiſtory reporteth, how <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Britaines,</hi> viz:<note place="margin">Li. 2. ca. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Si in tribus his obtemperare mihi vultis, vt Paſcha ſuo tempore celebre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, vt miniſterium baptizandi, quo Deo renaſcimur iuxta morem Romanae &amp; Apoſtolicae Eccleſiae compleatis, vt genti Angelorum vna nobiſcum praedicetis verbum Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, caetera, quae agitis quamuis moribus noſtris co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>traria, aequanimiter cuncta tolerabimus.</hi> By which their ſo earneſt diſſenting about theſe only matters of ſmaller importance, is moſt plainly ſignified their full agreement in all other ſubſtantiall, and head
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:18148:31"/> points of Faith; for the <hi>Brittaines,</hi> who contradicted <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſo earneſtly in theſe ſo few, &amp; ſmaler points, would neuer haue bine ſilent, but much the rather haue with-ſtood him in the other ſo many, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably much greater points of Faith, had they in like ſort diſagreed from him therin, which thing is alſo as yet more certainly euident, <hi>aſwell in that the Brittain Biſhops then confeſſed, that it was the right way of Iuſtice, &amp; righteouſnes, which Auſtine taught,</hi> (as <hi>Bede</hi> doth teſtifie;<note place="margin">Bed. hiſt li 2. ca. 2. Fulk. in his conf. of purg. pa. 335.</note>) As alſo for that <hi>Auſtine</hi> did, (as Mr.
<hi>Fulke</hi> affirmeth) at the laſt obtaine the aide of the British Bishops to the conuerſion of the <hi>Saxons;</hi> The ſame affirmeth
<hi>Holinſhead</hi> heretofore alleadged. So euidently therefore doth that Faith, which <hi>S. Auſtine</hi> taught vs, and which our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries acknowledge for Popish, demonſtrate in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall to be conſonante, and agreable with that Primitiue Faith, whereunto the <hi>Brittains</hi> of
<hi>VVales</hi> were, (as is confeſſed) conuerted in the Apoſtles times. Which pointe is alſo made euident by like further obſeruations of ſo many other remote na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, conuerted in the Apoſtles times, as namely of
<hi>Graecia,</hi> as appeareth by <hi>S. Pauls</hi> Epiſtles to ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry of that nation, as to the <hi>Corinthians, Epheſians, Theſſalonians; of Armenia,</hi> by <hi>S. Bartholomew;</hi> of <hi>India</hi> by <hi>Saint Thomas;</hi> which although they be in ſome things departed from the faith wherunto <pb n="51" facs="tcp:18148:31"/> they were firſt conuerted, yet by their remnant of Religion to this day preſerued, ſufficiently appee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, which faith it was whether, Catholicke or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtante, whereto they were at firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted; witnes hereof are the ſeuerall publike <hi>Liturgies</hi> of the
<hi>Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, Armenians, &amp;c.</hi> the which, trauailers affirme &amp; make ſo knowne &amp; certaine, as impudencie it ſelfe may not deny it.
<hi>Andrew Theuet</hi> an Author of greate credite in his
<hi>Coſmographie</hi> vniuerſall Printed in French at <hi>Paris</hi> Anno
1575.<note place="margin">Tom. 1. Fol. 137.</note> affirmeth vpon the experience of his trauailes, that he founde at <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> in the holy Paſsion weeke more then 4000. Chriſtians of ſeuerall Nations, as <hi>Abiſsines, Armenians, Monouites, Georgians of Perſia, Neſtorians, Iacobits, Sirians, Iauians, Butirians, Darians, men of Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi> moſt remote of all the Orientall <hi>India, &amp;c.</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe being ſole among them with an
<hi>Almaine</hi> of the Romane Church; The which Nations, (ſaith he)
<hi>Chantent la Meſſe auec pareille opinion ſur le Reall praeſence du corps &amp; ſang de noſtre Seigneur co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me nous la tenons,</hi> that is: Do celebrate Maſſe, holding the like opinion of the Reall preſence of the body and bloud of our Lord, as we (of the Latine Church) hould. Nothwithſtanding, (ſaith he) that they do not acknowledge either Pope or Cardinall, King or Emperor of ours, but profeſſe themſelues to haue receaued their ſacred miſteries from the <pb n="52" facs="tcp:18148:32"/> Apoſtles. The like teſtimonie giues the Proteſtante writer,<note place="margin">Pag.
22</note> 
               <hi>D. Philippus Nicholai</hi> in his comment. <hi>de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gno Christi</hi> of theſe remote Nations; by which fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſaid examples of ſo many remote Nations ſo farre diſtante each from other, conuerted vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly in the Apoſtles times, and agreeing ſo farre with vs, and againſt our aduerſaries, in ſo many principall points of Faith, is not obſcurely ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, that our now Catholike Religion is that Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Faith, which the Apoſtles themſelues firſt planted in all Nations.</p>
            <p>The Antiquitie and Prioritie of this our Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsion of our profeſſed Catholike doctrine thus shewed and handled, but in generall, is alſo made as yet much more probable, or rather euident throughout each particular, by that which our learned aduerſaries themſelues do acknowledge, chardging the moſt ancient Fathers their opinions in theſe points, as errours. To go through euery par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticular would be ouer tedious. But the Reader for better ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may read the <hi>Proteſtants Apologie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tract 1. Sect. 3. Subdi. 1</note> where he shall finde all things at large ſet downe, &amp; moſt cleerly and euidently handled. Forbearing therefore all other points, we will giue inſtance only in that pointe vndertaken chiefly in this our Application, viz: of Cath. Prieſthood.</p>
            <p>The Prieſthood of our ſpirituall Paſtors in this
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:18148:32"/> out Cath. Churche, who as, <hi>S. Aug.</hi> ſaith, are now, not improperly but properly called Prieſts in the Church:<note place="margin">De ciuit. Dei li. 20 cap 10.</note> &amp; to whome therefore the word <hi>Presbiter and Sacerdos</hi> are indifferently referred, (as likewiſe
<hi>S. August.</hi> there affirmeth) in reſpect of the Bleſſed Sacrament, which is by them offered to God vnder <hi>Chriſt</hi> the high Preeiſt, and in his ſteed &amp; place. (as <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> &amp; <hi>S. Cypr.</hi> do affirme) as the Churches externall and acceptable oblatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Ambr. in 1. Tim. ca. 4.14. S. Cypr. li. 2 Ep. 3</note> &amp; acknowledged by learned Proteſtants to haue bene for ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly offered, not only for theſe thouſand yeares laſt paſt, but alſo for ſo many other praece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Ages.</p>
            <p>For theſe laſt thouſand yeares it is a generall opinion amongſt Proteſtants.<note place="margin">Fol. 344.</note> Mr. <hi>Beacon</hi> in his Treatiſe intituled, <hi>The Reliques of Rome,</hi> affirmeth ſaying, The Maſſe was fully finished by <hi>Gregory</hi> the firſt about Anno 600 &amp;c. And from <hi>Charles the Greate</hi> vnto <hi>Charles the</hi> 5. the Maſſe raigned, as a moſt mightie Queene in all the Churches of the weſt part of the world. <hi>Melancth. lib.</hi> 4.<note place="margin">Fol.
186.</note> 
               <hi>Chronic. in Henr.</hi> 4 ſaith of <hi>S. Greg.</hi> that he allowed by publike authority the ſacrifice of Chriſts Body &amp; Bloud, not only for the liuing, but alſo for the dead; The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame is affirmed by many other Proteſtante writers. Before <hi>Gregorie,</hi> was <hi>Pelagius,</hi> whome <hi>Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus loc. com. de Caena Domini, pag.</hi> 336. And Mr.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18148:33"/> 
               <hi>Simonds</hi> vpon the Reuel. pag. 81. (both of them being Proteſtante writers) do directly charge with the opinion of the Maſſe helping the dead. <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machus</hi> was Bishop of Rome Anno 501. of whome the Century-writers ſay,<note place="margin">Cent. 6. ca. 10. col. 664. Fol. 27.</note> 
               <hi>Notas Antichriſti &amp; hic ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit, Miſſam enim in formam redigit.</hi> Before him was <hi>S. Leo</hi> Anno 440. of whome Mr.
<hi>Bale</hi> in his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant of Popes ſaith: <hi>Leo</hi> the firſt allowed the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Maſſe, &amp;c. Before <hi>Leo</hi> was the fourth and fift, Councell of <hi>Carthage</hi> at which was preſent <hi>S. Auguſtine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> the one reproued by <hi>Pelargus in his Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la fidei</hi> for allowing prayer,<note place="margin">Pag. 13.</note> &amp; Maſſe for the dead, the other by <hi>Luke Oſiander cent,</hi> 4
<hi>pag.</hi> 16. for that in the 27. Canon of this fourth Councell mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was made of Prayers, &amp; oblations for the dead, Before theſe Councells was
<hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> Anno 370. whome the Cent. writers cent. 4. ca. 4. col.
295. Do charge with not writing well <hi>de Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione &amp; applicatione pro mortuis.</hi> Before him was <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory Niſsen</hi> of the Greeke Church Anno 340, whom <hi>Andraeas Craſtonius</hi> in his booke againſt <hi>Bellarmine</hi> chargeth for allowing the Euchariſte to be likewiſe a ſacrifice.<note place="margin">Craſto. de opifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio Miſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſae. lib. 1. Sect 146.</note> Alſo <hi>S. Cyrill.</hi> of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> another Father of the Greekes florished Anno 320. <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinianus</hi> chargeth him for his acknowledgment of Maſſe,<note place="margin">Hoſp. in Hiſt. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cram. pag. 167.</note> &amp; Prayer for the dead. Before theſe times liued <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> Anno 240. of whome the Cent.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:18148:33"/> writers do ſay: cent. 3. cap. 4. col. 89. <hi>Sacerdotem vice Chriſti fungi in Coena Domini ſuperſtitioſe aſſerit Cyprianus.</hi> The ſame affirmeth Mr. <hi>Fulk.</hi> againſt
<hi>Sanders:</hi> pag, 100 Before him liued <hi>Tertullian</hi> Anno 220. whom
<hi>Oſiander</hi> cent. 3. lib. 1. cap. 5. and Mr. <hi>Fulk</hi> in his Conf. of Purg. pa, 265. do charge for allowing of Maſſe for the dead. Before him was <hi>Irenaeus</hi> Anno 170. whom <hi>Caluine</hi> chargeth for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming the ſacrifice of <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> to haue bene a figure of the ſacrifice of the Maſſe.<note place="margin">Cal lib. de vera Eccl. refor. Cent 2. cap. 4. col. 63.</note> Before him liued <hi>Ignatius,</hi> the Apoſtles vndoubted Scoller An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no 90 whome the Cent. writers do charge for ſaying, that it was not lawfull to offer, or to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice without a Bishop. Laſtly Mr. <hi>Beacon</hi> in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of Rome, being a great diuine amongſt our Aduerſaries, affirmeth ſeriouſly ſaying,<note place="margin">Fol. 344.</note> the Maſſe was begotten, conceaued, &amp; borne anon after the Apoſtles times, if all be true that
<hi>Hiſtoriographers</hi> do write. This ſame ſaith <hi>Sebastianus Francus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb Ep. de ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rog ſtat. Eccl.</note> and
<hi>Hoſpinianus</hi> in Hiſt. Sacram. li. 1. ca. 6. pag. 20. af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, that in the very Apoſtles times this was the opinion of many men.</p>
            <p>Now therefore may it vouch ſafe your wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes to conſider duly this Priority of our poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsion, and ſucceſsiue continuance of this our Cath. doctrine, deduced from the Apoſtles times, euen our Enemies being Iudges: And take heed <pb n="56" facs="tcp:18148:34"/> of that ſaying of <hi>S. Aug. in no, &amp; vet. Teſt. quaeſt.</hi> no. Heretickes, (ſaith he) do trouble &amp; breake the order of ſucceeding Bishops begunne by <hi>S. Petr.</hi> and brought downe by ofſpring, one Bishop ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding another, and ſo challenge vnto themſelues a certaine order with out beginning.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>SECTION VI.</hi> OF PRAESCRIPTION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F Praeſcription it ſelf, wherof no me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory occurreth to the contrary, be a matter of any importance, with your honors, (Right graue &amp; Learned Iudges) you shall then here finde our now profeſſed Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Religion deduced from the Apoſtles ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, &amp; by your learned writers confeſſed. Surely I perſwade my ſelfe that if any one Baron, Earle, or Duke in England could shew, but half of theſe yeares, we can shew for the continuance and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsion of any temporall ſtate, Lordship, or land in England, he would highly eſteeme therof, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by make a glorious defence againſt any wrangling companion, that should pretend theſame, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue him therof, if he should truely ſay, &amp; proue, (as we do the cauſe of our Church;) neither were <pb n="57" facs="tcp:18148:34"/> it credible, that the Iudges of his cauſe should giue the definitiue againſt him; But no man can preſcribe any ſuch time in temporall matters, and therfore are they well called temporall, for that they cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge in a litle time; No Dukedome or Earledome, continuing lightly 3. or 4. generations together in any one name or family, as may be eaſily ſeene in <hi>Camdens</hi> ſtory, where he taketh vpon him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the Earles, &amp; Dukes that had their ſtates &amp; titles ouer ſuch a shire. But, as for matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Almighty God hath giuen another manner of force, vnto ſucceſsion both of men &amp; faith; as for example, in the law of nature he made theſame to endure, by only tradition without writing for more then 2500. yeares vnder the Ancient Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arches before, &amp; after the Flood of <hi>Noe.</hi> And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward againe in the written lawe, the iewes conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued the poſſeſsion of their religion by ſucceſsion of Bishops, and Eccleſiaſticall Gouernors from
<hi>Moyſes</hi> vnto Chriſt aboue 1500. yeares, not with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtanding of all the varietie of times, &amp; calamities. And no leſſe from Chriſt to our age, hath he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued the ſame in a much more gratious ſorte, &amp; manner, notwithſtanding ſo many mutations, both in the <hi>Romane Empire,</hi> &amp; all other Realmes &amp; Kingdomes, &amp; yet euer hath ſucceſsion of Paſtours &amp; vnion of faith remained,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:18148:35"/>Firſt therfore our aduerſaries will not ſticke vpon the firſt 100. yeares, which reached to <hi>S. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories</hi> time, but will graunt vnto vs that the Maſſe, &amp; Catholike Prieſthood was a generall doctrine throughout the whole world.<note place="margin">Pow. Pag
105.</note> So Mr. <hi>Powell</hi> in his conſiderations of the Papish reaſons: I grant (ſaith he) that from the yeare of Chriſt 605. the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant company of popery hath bene very viſible, &amp; perſpicuous.<note place="margin">Perk. pa. 307.</note> Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> in his expoſition of the creed affirmeth, that from <hi>Gregories</hi> daies to
<hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> (which was 900. yeares) the Popish hereſy had ſpredd it ſelf ouer the whole earth. The like acknowledgement doth make <hi>Simon de Voyon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Fulk</hi> &amp; others heretofore cited.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Nap. pag. 68.</note>Mr. <hi>Napper,</hi> that ſo greatly commended aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, in his Treatiſe vpon the Reuel. dedicated to the K. Maieſty, granted vs 1260. yeares of preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſaying, that betwixt the yeare of Chriſt 300. &amp; 316.
<hi>Anti-chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> raigne began raigning vniuerſally, &amp; without any debatable contradictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 1260. yeares; &amp; theſame affirmeth Mr.
<hi>Brocard</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Mr. <hi>Gifford</hi> againſt the
<hi>Browniſts</hi> pag. 38. graunteth vs 1300,<note place="margin">Fo.
110.</note> &amp; odder yeares ſaying: to offer oblation for the dead was generall in the Church lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g before the daies of <hi>S. Auſtine,</hi> as appeareth in <hi>S. Cyprian. &amp; Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tull.</hi> who liued about the yeare
240. <hi>Hamelmannus de Traditionibus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fol 741.</note> reacheth vp to <hi>S. Denis of Areopag.</hi> 
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:18148:35"/> who liued in the in the Apoſtles times, ſaying, that <hi>Denis</hi> did write much of Churches, of Altars, of places ſanctified, of Conſecrations, Monkes, and ſundry Ceremonies. <hi>Sebaſtianus Francus Epiſt. de abrogandis ſtatut. Eccleſ.</hi> ſaith, that immediatly after the Apoſtles times the Maſſe begun. <hi>Hoſpinianus in hiſt. Sacram.</hi> lib. 1. ca. 6. affirmeth, that it was euen in the Apoſtles times, they being yet aliue. Mr.
<hi>Aſcham,</hi> a prime proteſtant in his Apol. <hi>pro caena Dom.</hi> pag. 31. acknowledged, that no beginning therof can. be shewed. Mr. <hi>Gab. Powell,</hi> pag. 43. in his conſideration of the <hi>Papiſtes Supplication;</hi> being prouoked; that, if our Catholike doctrine be er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, then to tell vs when it came in? who was the Author of it? &amp;c. Anſwereth thereto acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſaying. We cannot tell by whome, or at what time the Enemie did ſow it, neither indeed do we know, who was the firſt Author of euery one of your blaſphemous opinions. And Mr. <hi>VVhita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> in Reſp. ad Camp. rat. 7. pag. 101. confeſſeth, that the Romane Churches change cannot eaſily be tould.</p>
            <p>Now if that rule,<note place="margin">Aug Ep. 118.</note> or proofe of Apoſtolical do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>S. Aug.</hi> be true: viz. Whatſoeuer opinion is not knowne to haue begun ſince the Apoſtles times, theſame is not new or ſecondary, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, it is originall from the Apoſtles themſelues. <pb n="60" facs="tcp:18148:36"/> The which Rule ſaith Mr.
<hi>VVhitgift,</hi> (ſome times Archb of Canterb.) in his defence pag. 352. was of credit with the writers of our time, namely with Mr. <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> Mr. <hi>Caluine,</hi> &amp; Mr. <hi>Gualter;</hi> and ſurelie, (ſaith he) I thinke no learned man doth diſſent from them: the which Rule he likewiſe vrgeth againſt Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> his Puritane Brother, in defence of the names <hi>Metropolitanes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cartwr. ag. whilg. pag
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>03. &amp; 352.</note> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> to whome Mr. <hi>Cartwr.</hi> anſweareth ſaying. I appeale to the Iudgement of all men, if this be not to bring in Poperie againe, to allow of <hi>S. Auguſtins</hi> ſaying, &amp;c. Further he affirmeth, that therby a window is open to bring in all Popery. Therfore ſeeing, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>S. Auguſtins</hi> rule, the opinion &amp; doctrine, whoſe beginning is not knowne, &amp; whoſe Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity cannot be found, is a proofe of Apoſtolike Doctrine; it followeth, that the opinion, whoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning is knowne, the Antiquity &amp; Author ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of found, is a ſufficient proofe of falſe doctrine. And hence it is that
<hi>S. Hierome</hi> ſaith: To reduce an hereſie to a beginning is a confutation of it.<note place="margin">Hiero. ad Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiphont.</note> And ſeing, that our aduerſaries ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> shew no beginning or Author of the foreſaid pointe of Catholike Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, (yea not of any one neceſſary, and eſſentiall Article of Catholike doctrine;) &amp; on the other part, ſeing we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reduce euery pointe of aduerſe doctrine to his beginning, Author, time &amp; place fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt <pb n="61" facs="tcp:18148:36"/> to this day, according to the promiſe made by God himſelf to his Catholike Church, that Paſtors,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.12. Iſa. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.6.</note> &amp; Doctors muſt be in the Church till the Conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Saints, who shalbe as watchmen all the day and all the night, for euer they shall not hould their peace, but shall alwayes reſiſt falſe opinions, &amp; innouations with open reprehenſion. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequently it followeth, this our Catholike doctrine, wherto we were ſo many Ages ſince conuerted, to be no new or ſecondary, ſince the Apoſtles times, but truely primitiue, and vndoubtedly Apoſtolike. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, our aduerſaries doctrine to be new, ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary, falſe, and Apoſtaticke. And this concerning
<hi>Praeſcription.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>SECTION VII.</hi> OF CONTINVALL CLAIME.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F <hi>Continuall Claime</hi> be a matter amongſt you, wherby Right &amp; title are preſerued: It is more then euident, that this our Catholike Church hath bene euer wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, &amp; ready, euen within the yeare, &amp; day ſo to preſerue her right in this, and other points, againſt all Sects and hereſies whatſoeuer, and howſoeuer deuided otherwiſe among themſelues, did generally <pb n="62" facs="tcp:18148:37"/> conſpire to oppoſe themſelues, as againſt their ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall enemie. This is euident to this day in <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſtes, Swenckfeldians, Libertines, Antrinitarians, etc.</hi> Who thinke the reformation of Religion to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt ſpecially in the abnegation of our Catholike Faith, terming themſelues in ſuch reſpect reformed Churches, and euery one of them thinking them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſo much more reformed then others, by how much they are further, then others, diſſenting from our Catholike Religion, it needeth no better proofe, then that of the Proteſtants &amp; Puritanes in England. We haue not bene wanting to this
<hi>Continuall Claime</hi> before <hi>Luthers</hi> time, by reaſon of our former confeſſed quiet poſſeſsion euen in the iudgement of our very aduerſaries. And our need ſince his time hath bene but in ſome countries, in which our <hi>Claime,</hi> hath bene ſo dailie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, as we hould it needleſſe to proue the ſame: ſo that our aduerſaries are forced to ſay, their Church was for many yeares inuiſible, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that promiſe made by God himſelfe to his Church,<note place="margin">Eſay
62.2.</note> ſaying: vpon thy Walles ô Hieruſalem haue I ſet watchmen all the day &amp; night, for euer they shall not be ſilent.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 191. 188.</note>Mr. Napper in his booke vpon the Reuelation dedicated to the Kings Maieſtie, affirmeth, that this abiding of Gods Temple ſo long latent, and <pb n="63" facs="tcp:18148:37"/> obſcure is moſt certaine: Noe true viſible Church, nor ſincere doctrine publiquely opened, that any man may haue acceſſe vnto. Againe, from the yeare of Chriſt 316.<note place="margin">Pag. 161.</note> God hath withdrawne his Church from open aſſemblies into the harts of particular godly men, where it abode inuiſible to theſe our daies, the ſpace of 1260. yeares, acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging likewiſe, that during the foreſaid ſpace of 1260 yeares, the Catholike Romane Church did poſſeſſe the foreſaid <hi>Continuall Claime,</hi> affirming that from <hi>Conſtantines</hi> time till thoſe our daies euen
1260. years the Pope, &amp; his Clergie haue poſſeſſed the outward viſible Church of Chriſtians.<note place="margin">Pag 43.</note> Mr. <hi>Gab. Powell</hi> in his conſideration of the Papiſtes ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, ſaith: We cannot tell by whome, or at what time the enemie did ſowe, &amp;c. (meaning our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike doctrine.) Mr. <hi>Fulk.</hi> in his Reioined,<note place="margin">Pag. 265.</note> being vrged with this demand, I anſweare (quoth he) my text ſaith it was a miſterie not reuealed, &amp; therfore could not be at the firſt preached againſt. And Mr. D. <hi>Field</hi> of the Church anſwereth our demaund in this manner, ſaying:<note place="margin">Pag.
8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The errours of the Church of Rome were ſo brought in, that both they, that were the Authors of them, &amp; others, that neuer fell into them were of one <hi>Communion,</hi> and therefore it is moſt abſurd to require vs to shew theſe circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, viz: concerning any beginning of our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike <pb n="64" facs="tcp:18148:38"/> doctrine ſince the Apoſtles times. But I appeale to your honors graue Iudgments, if the anſwer of this diuine be not more abſurd, then the demaund. But ſuch euaſorie arguments as theſe, be all we can gett of our Aduerſaries.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Hier. 33.18.</note>The Prophet
<hi>Hieremie</hi> ſpeaking of the Paſtors of Gods Church, ſaith: that they shalbe multiplied to miniſter vnto him, not with interrupted ſeaso<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, but continually euen as the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> ſaith, from month to month,<note place="margin">Iſa. 66.21. Dan. 2.44.</note> &amp; from Sabaoth to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth: neither, (ſaith <hi>Daniell</hi>) shall this kingdome of the Church be giuen ouer to another people, but shall ſtand for euer,<note place="margin">Iſay. 60.</note> Againe <hi>Iſay</hi> ſaith in plaine termes, that Kings shall miniſter vnto the Church, &amp; her grates shalbe continually open, neither day nor night shall they be shutt, that men may bring to her the riches of the Gentiles. Hence it is, that one of your writers confeſſeth,<note place="margin">The ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of one of their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</note> that if our faith hath bene interrupted, (quoth he) ſince Chriſts time ſo much as one yeare, month, or day-were ſufficient to proue vs no part of the Church of God, ſo Mr. <hi>VVhite</hi> in his booke, the way to the true Church, pag. 86.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 16.</note>The like promiſes are mentioned in the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament: Vpon this Rocke, (ſaith our Sauiour) will I build my Church, and hell gates shall not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile againſt it. Againe: Lo I am with you euen to <pb n="65" facs="tcp:18148:38"/> the conſummation of the world. And
<hi>S. Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. vlt.</note> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the priuiledges granted to the Church, ſaith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He gaue ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.</note> and other ſome Euangeliſtes, and other ſome Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and Doctors to the conſummation of the Saints, vnto the worke of the miniſtrie, vnto the edifying of the body of Chriſt, vntill we meete all vnto the vnity of faith, &amp; knowledge of the loue of God into a perfect man, into the meaſure of the age of the fulneſſe of Chriſt: That is, according to all Expoſitors euen Proteſtants,<note place="margin">Cal. Inſt ca. 8. Melan. in loc. com. Fulk. againſt the Rhem. Teſtam.</note> vnto the worlds end. But thoſe miniſteriall offices of Paſtors and Doctors, &amp;c. cannot be exerciſed, where the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors know not their sheepe, nor the sheepe their Paſtors; which could not be when the Church was inuiſible, &amp; withdrawne from open aſſemblies to the harts of particular godly men for the ſpace of 1260. yeares, as Mr. <hi>Napper</hi> affirmeth on the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel, pag. 161. Neither can it be ſaid, which D. <hi>Field</hi> in his foreſaid Anſwer affirmeth, that they, who where of the true Church, and they that were not, were of one Communion: ſeing that no man can be ſaued, that inwardly houldeth one Religion and onwardly profeſſeth another, as our Sauiour teacheth
<hi>Math.</hi> 10, and the Apoſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. For ſo Mr. D.
<hi>Field</hi> will haue me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be in the true Church, &amp; yet not be ſaued. Which implieth a flat contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, <pb n="66" facs="tcp:18148:39"/> and ſo he imagines abſurdities in other mens ſayings, but he ſeeth not the contradictions in his owne. If <hi>S. Auſtine</hi> were aliue, he would deale in no better termes with theſe our aduerſaries, then he did diſputing againſt the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> for maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a pretended inuiſible Church: theſe be his wordes:<note place="margin">Aug. in Pſa 101.</note> Belike (ſaith he) that Church, which was the Church of all Nations, is now no more, she is gone, she is loſt, this ſay they that are not in her; ô impudent ſpeech, she is not, becauſe you are not in her; take heed leaſt thou thy ſelf be not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for she shalbe, though thou be not: And then doth he bring in the Church ſpeaking thus: How long time shall I be in this world? Tell me for their ſakes that ſay, there hath bene a Church, but now there is none, she is become Apoſtata, she is bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed away from all nations. It was shewed me. Who shewed me? euen the way himſelf. When? Lo I am with you euen to the conſummation of the world. Neither can it be ſaid, that <hi>S. Auſtine</hi> ſpeaketh of a Church inuiſible, for that neuer to haue perished the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> did willingly admit, as here alſo he te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth. What other argument (I pray you) did Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vſe againſt the Iewes to proue, that the <hi>Meſsias</hi> was come, but that theſe promiſes of the Prophets were fulfilled, not in their Sinagogs, which were for ſo long time together ſcattered, theſe be <hi>Luthers</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:18148:39"/> wordes. <hi>Quomodo hoc quadrabit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luther. lib. de Iudae is Tom. 7. printed at Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temb.</note>
               <hi>legem ipſorum eſſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raturam in aeternum, cum iam annis plus</hi>
1500. <hi>ſacerdotium templum, cultus, omnia deleta &amp; funditus euerſa iaceant, ſupra modum &amp; vehementer ridiculum eſt, quod nos Gentes, Iudaei perſuadere volunt ad ſuam inter-mortuam abſoletam legem, quae nunc per annos</hi> 1500, <hi>antiquata &amp; abolita eſt, &amp;c.</hi> Was not this pretended latencie and Inuiſibility cauſe of the reuolt of ſundry of the learnedeſt men among our aduerſaries? <hi>Bernardine Ochine,</hi> (whom all Italy could not match for lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,<note place="margin">Cal. lib. de ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</note> as <hi>Caluine</hi> ſaith) hauing entred but into exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of this forſaid ſcruple, began here vpon to ſtagger, &amp; become perplexed, ſaying: When I did conſider how Chriſt by his power, wiſdome,<note place="margin">Bern. Ochin. in praef. ſuorum Dialog.</note> and goodnes had founded &amp; eſtabished his Church, washed it with his bloud, &amp; enriched it with his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; and againe I had diſcerned, how the ſame was vtterly ouer throwne, I could not but wonder, and being deſirous to know the cauſe, I found there had bene Popes, In ſo much as hee proceeded from this conceipt of the Popes preuailing, further to teach Circumciſion and Poligamie; in defence of the which laſt point, he wrote a booke in <hi>Italian.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In hiſt. Georgij Dauid is printed at Anno 1568.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid George</hi> the <hi>Hollander,</hi> conſidering the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes made by God himſelf of the continuance of his Church, &amp; not fulfilled in the Proteſtants Church, became a blaſphemours Apoſtata, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, <pb n="68" facs="tcp:18148:40"/> our B. Sauiour to be a ſeducer: ſaying; If the doctrine of Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles had bene true &amp; perfect, the Church, which they planted, &amp;c. should haue continued, &amp;c. The like befell vnto <hi>Sebaſtian Caſtalion</hi> a learned Caluiniſt,<note place="margin">Caſtal. in the preface to his Latin Bible.</note> who ſtagge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in his Religion, fell to doubtfull ſearches of our Chriſtian Faith. Neither is England wanting examples of diuers Profeſſours, who haue in the end denied the diuinitie of Chriſt, whereof in Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time two were burned at Norwich.<note place="margin">Rogers of the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland pag. 9.</note> By theſe examples your <hi>VViſedomes</hi> may eaſily perceiue the inueterate, and more then <hi>Vatinian</hi> hatred, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with preiudice of opinion hath ſo ſtrongly poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed our Aduerſaries againſt our Church &amp; Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that not diſcerning themſelues able to iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their owne Church in accomplishment hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto of thoſe praedictions, which are fore told of Chriſts true Church, many and not the meaneſt of them: yea rather then they would yeald to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue in this common danger their Chriſtian pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion by acknowledgment of our Catholike Church, in which the ſaid praedictions are moſt clearly accomplished, haue finally, <hi>(ô tempora! ô mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res!)</hi> betaken themſelues to moſt dreadfull Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſy.</p>
            <p>Therefore we appeale to your graue Iudgemente and ſerious conſiderations, if this ſolate entry (ſince <pb n="69" facs="tcp:18148:40"/> King
<hi>Henry</hi> the 8. time only) made by our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries at their owne hand, on this our poſſeſsion, be not againſt all courſe of law, and they conuict of ſecret and ſtolne Diſſeiſnie. And thus much briefly concerning <hi>Continuall Claime.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>SECTION VIII.</hi> OF THE DOVBTFVLNESSE of the ſtatute law.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OREOVER if where the letter of your Statute law appeareth to be in ſome caſes doubtfull, you hould that ſenſe and vnderſtanding therof for moſt reaſonable, which is found moſt agreable with the knowne anſwerable practiſe of the enſuing times. Then your Wiſdomes shall find the doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full letter, (whether of ſcripture, or of certaine ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure ſayings of the Fathers) made plaine on our part by the anſwerable practiſe of all ſucceeding times concerning this pointe of Catholike Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, (and other points of our forſaid Catholike doctrine) by conſent of Councells, iudgment of Fathers, and confeſsion of our aduerſaries, as hath bene moſt plainly heretofore throughout demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated. For what fairer euidences can be deſired,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:18148:41"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:18148:41"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:18148:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> then the conſent of 18. Generall Councells, viz: of <hi>Nice</hi> vnder Pope
<hi>Silueſter</hi> about the yeare 325. at the which were preſent 318. Bishops: Of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> the firſt vnder <hi>Pope Damaſus</hi> in the yeare 384. Of <hi>Epheſus</hi> the firſt vnder Pope
<hi>Caeleſtine</hi> about the yeare 434. at the which were preſent 220 Prelates: Of <hi>Calcedon</hi> vnder Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the great about the yeare 454. at which were preſent 630. Bishops. Of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> in the yeare 553. ended vnder Pope <hi>Vigilio,</hi> at which were preſent
165. Bishops: Of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> the 3. in the yeare 681. vnder Pope
<hi>Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thon;</hi> being there preſent. 290. Bishops: Of <hi>Nice</hi> the 2. vnder Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> in the yeare 781. there being preſent 370. Bishops: Of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> the 4. in the yeare 819. vnder Pope
<hi>Adrian</hi> the 2. at which were preſent 375. Bishops: Of
<hi>Lateran</hi> the firſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Pope <hi>Caliſt</hi> the 2. in the yeare
1119. at which were preſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>00. Bishops. The 3. Councell of
<hi>Lateran</hi> vnder <hi>Alexander</hi> the 3. in the yeare 1180. there being preſent 300. Bishops: The 4. Councell of <hi>Lateran</hi> vnder Pope
<hi>Innocent</hi> 3. in the yeare 1215. in which were preſent 1200. Bishops: The firſt Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell of <hi>Lions</hi> vnder <hi>Innocent</hi> 4, in the yeare
1245. at which were preſent 140. Bishops. The 2. Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Lions</hi> in the yeare 1274. vnder Pope <hi>Greg.</hi> the 10. being preſent there 700. Bishops. The Councell of <hi>Vienna</hi> vnder <hi>Clement</hi> the 5. in the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:18148:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> yeare 1311. there being preſent 300. Bishops: The Councell of <hi>Florence</hi> vnder <hi>Eugenius</hi> the 4. in the yeare 1459. there being preſent 141. Bishops. The 5. Councell of <hi>Lateran</hi> vnder Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the 10. in the yeare 1517. being preſent 114. Bishops. The Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> in the yeare 1545. vnder <hi>Paul</hi> the 3. and continued vnder <hi>Iulius</hi> the 4. <hi>Marcellus</hi> the 2. and
<hi>Paull</hi> the 4. and finished vnder <hi>Pius</hi> the 4. in the yeare
1563. Theſe be all Generall and approued Councells, one ſucceeding another from age to age. Neither were there wanting throughout all theſe Centuries of yeares, Fathers &amp; Doctors, who did maintaine this our Catholike doctrine. For in the 1 Century were <hi>Martiall, Denis of Areopag.</hi> who were in the firſt hundred yeares after Chriſt: In the 2. Centurie <hi>Ignatius, Policarpus, Iuſtinus, Irenaeus:</hi> In the 3. Cent. were <hi>Clemens Alex, Cyprianus, Arnobius.</hi> In the 4. Cent. <hi>Lactantius, Victor, Afer, Hilarins, Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius, Cyrillus Baſilius, Epiphanius, Gregorius Niſſ, Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorius Nazian. Optatus, Ambroſ. Ruffinus.</hi> In the 5. Cent. were
<hi>Chryſostomus, Hieronimus, Auguſtinus, Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus, Caſsianus, Theodoretus, Chryſologus, Hilarius, Leo Magnus, Proſper, Fulgentius</hi> In the 6. Cent. were <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius Emiſſ. Caſsiodorus, Climacus, Gregorius Turonenſis, Euagarius, Gregorius Magnus.</hi> In the 7. Cent. <hi>Leon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Sophronius, Iſidorus Hiſpal. Leander, Branlius, Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dephonſus.</hi> In the 8. Cent, <hi>Venerabilis Beda, Ioannes<pb n="72" facs="tcp:18148:43"/> Damaſcenus, Paulus Diaconus, Alcuinus, Vſuardus, Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus Aquilienſis.</hi> In the 9. Cent. <hi>Haymo, Rabanus, Ioannes Diaconus, Theophilactus, Anaſtaſius, Hincmarus.</hi> In the 10. Cent. <hi>Odo cluniac. Ado Viennenſis, Lint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prandus, Radulphus, Rathodius, Abbas Floriacenſis.</hi> In the 11. Cent,
<hi>Petrus Damianus, Humbertus, Lanfran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, Anſelmus, Algerus, Oecumen. Bruno, Iuo.</hi> In the 12. Cent. <hi>cedrenus, Rupertus, Bernardus, Euthymius, Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tianus, Richardus de S. Victore.</hi> In the 13. Cent. <hi>caeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, Alexander de Hales, Albertus, Thomas Aquinas, cantipratenſis, Durandus, Scotus, Bonauentura.</hi> In the 14. Cent. <hi>Nicephorus, Paludanus, Aureolus, Occam, Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranus.</hi> In the 15. Cent. <hi>Thomas de Kemp Laur. Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinianus, Bernardinns, Beſſarius, Toſtanis.</hi> In the 16. Cent, <hi>Ioannes Eccius, Thomas Morus, Roffenſis, A caſtro, Sanderus, Hoſius, Alanus, Driedo, Baronius, Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larminus, Suarez, Salmeron,</hi> and many others; by the teſtimonies of theſe Fathers renowned for their vertue, pietie, &amp; learning throughout all the world, (euen our aduerſaries being Iudges) their workes bearing witneſſe, you shall find the doubtfull letter of Scripture or of certaine obſcure ſayings of ſome Fathers made plaine by the anſwerable practiſe of all theſe precedent ages, concerning this point of Cath. Prieſthood, yea they being Prieſts the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. Now as
<hi>Tertullian lib. praeſcr. adu. haereſ, confingant tale quid haeretici.</hi> Let heretiques deuiſe ſuch a prooffe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="section">
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:18148:43"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECTION IX.</hi> OF HIGH COVRTES of Iudgment.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>ESIDES all this, there are eſtablished with you for the finall ending of all ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing controuerſies &amp; ſuites of law, high Courts of Iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to giue definitine ſentence; and theſame ſo giuen, not by the law it ſelfe, but by your ſelues, placed as Iudges to pronounce &amp; determine, what is the law, againſt which ſentence ſo once orderly giuen in your hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gheſt court of Iudgement, &amp; perliament, no writt of errour or appeale lieth, wherby to ſupport the partie ſo conuicted in the further humor of his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied &amp; endleſſe contention. Therfore if high Courtes &amp; perliament be authenticall, and of ſo much credit with you, then you shall find on our behalf ſo many generall Councells, iudgemente of Fathers, (euen in the time of the primitiue Church) concerning this point of Catholike Prieſthood, (&amp; other points of controuerſie) pronunced and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined againſt <hi>Nouelliſts,</hi> and heretikes of thoſe ancient times. <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> witneſſeth of the
<hi>Noua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 1. de Paen. cap. 2.</note> who denied, that Prieſts could remit ſinnes; <pb n="74" facs="tcp:18148:44"/> And <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> of <hi>Aerius</hi> for denying the ſacrifice of the Euchariſt for the dead;<note place="margin">Haer. 53.</note> For the which D.
<hi>Field</hi> a Proteſtant diuine ſaith,<note place="margin">Field of the Chur. l. 3. c. 29. pag. 138.</note> that <hi>Aerius</hi> was iuſtly condemned. All theſe twelue Councells before al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged by vs in ſetting downe of our Iury are moſt plaine in this point, &amp; neede no more proofe, then what hath bene there ſaid. Now if one high Court or parliament gathered of the moſt ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and wiſeſt men of one Kingdome be of ſo great force, that no place of contention, writ of errour or appeale remaineth to the partie once conuicted, shall not a generall Councell gathered, not of the wiſeſt &amp; learnedeſt men of one King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome only, but of many Kingdomes, and aſsiſted by the holy Ghoſt, (ô shall it not) haue no force, nor no credit for the finall ending of arriſing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies, &amp; contentions in matters of Religion? but notwithſtanding the ſentence pronounced &amp; arreſt giuen, yet it shalbe lawfull for euery one to follow his priuate iudgement, appealing to the written law of only Scripture; the which courſe your owne anſwerable groundes, &amp; principles do ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly informe you, that their endeuour herein is no other then abſurde, prepoſterous, &amp; infinitly contentious. Who is ſo blinde, as ſeeth not this to be the very ſame eſcape, &amp; flight of the
<hi>Nouelliſts</hi> of theſe our times? Thus Mr. <hi>Cartwright,</hi> (the
<hi>Puritane</hi> 
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:18148:44"/> Brother in Mr <hi>VVhitgifts</hi> defence pag. 111.) auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Proteſtants arguments. In this ſort is
<hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za</hi> himſelf noted to euade, ſaying;<note place="margin">Bancro. ſurvey. pag. 219.</note> If any shall op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe againſt my expoſition of the authoritie of certaine of the Ancient Fathers: <hi>ad verbum Dei pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoco.</hi> I do appeale to the word. Where vpon Mr. <hi>Bancroff<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> ſomtimes Bish. of Canterb<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> inferreth, ſaying: How crankis
<hi>Beza</hi> with the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? Thus the <hi>Browniſtes of Amſterdam</hi> (in their Apologie pag. 103.) labour to shrowde themſelues. Thus do the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> ſeeke to eſcape. Thus alſo doth
<hi>Socimus</hi> giue the ſlip in defence of his errour againſt the diuinity of Chriſt, ſaying to his Proteſt.<note place="margin">Socimus in lib. de Chriſti natura contra Volanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pag. 2.</note> aduerſarij
<hi>Volanus:</hi> we propound to vs in the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion none for Maſter or Interpreter, but only the holy Ghoſt, &amp;c. We do not thinke, that we are to ſtand to Iudgement of any man, though neuer ſo learned; of any Councells, though in shew neuer ſo holy and lawfully aſſembled; of any viſible Church, though neuer ſo perfect and vniuerſall, &amp;c. thus he.</p>
            <p>This kind of tergiuerſation vnder pretence of only Scripture, is, &amp; hath bene the ordinary euaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherby almoſt all Nouelliſts of preſent, &amp; former times haue dalie exempted themſelues from all authoritie of contrary Iudgemente. Hence it is, that there be ſo many Sects amongſt the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants <pb n="76" facs="tcp:18148:45"/> in England, &amp; other countreis. Hence it is, that many of the bookes of the ſcripture it ſelfe are reiected, euen by the chiefeſt Proteſtants, as <hi>S. Pauls</hi> Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> the Epiſtle of <hi>S. Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes,</hi> &amp;
<hi>S. Iude,</hi> the 2. of <hi>S. Peter,</hi> the 2. &amp; 3. of <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> &amp; the Apocalipſe, by <hi>Luther, Brentius, Kemnitius,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Magdeburgians.</hi> Hence it is, that the manifold, variable, and different tranſlations of Scripture, the tranſlation of the new Teſtament by <hi>Luther</hi> is condemned by <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> ſaying: <hi>ad Lutherum de Sacram.</hi> pag. 412. Thou <hi>Luther</hi> doſt corrupt the word of God,<note place="margin">Hoſpin. in hiſt. Sacram. Parte al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera. fol 183. Beza in reſp. Caſtal. Beza in Annot. in Matt.</note> &amp;c.
<hi>Luther</hi> in like manner doth reiect the tranſlations of
<hi>Zuinglius.</hi> The tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſett forth by <hi>Oecolampadinis,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Diuines</hi> of <hi>Baſile</hi> is reproued by <hi>Beza,</hi> calling it wicked, and altogether differing from the mind of the Holy Ghoſt, The tranſlation of <hi>Caſtalio,</hi> ſo much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by Proteſtants, is condemned by <hi>Beza.</hi> As being ſacrilegious, wicked, and Ethnicall. And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Caluines</hi> tranſlation, the learned Proteſtant Writer <hi>Carolus Molinaeus</hi> in tranſlat. Teſt. noui part. 12, fol. 110. ſaith thereof; <hi>Caluine in his Harmony</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the text of the Goſpell to leape vp &amp; downe, he vſeth violence to the letter of the Goſpell, and beſides this, addeth to the Text. As touching
<hi>Beza</hi> his tranſlation, the foreſaid <hi>Molinaeus ibidem</hi> part.
20 30. &amp;c. ſaith of him; He actually changed the text,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:18148:45"/> And <hi>Caſtalio,</hi> that learned <hi>Caluinist</hi> ſaith of <hi>Beza,</hi> that to note all his errours in tranſlation would require a great volume. All which confirmeth the Kings Maieſties Graue and learned cenſure in thinking the <hi>Geneua</hi> tranſlation to be worſt of all.<note place="margin">In the ſum of the confer. before the K. Maieſty, pag. 46.</note> And concerning the English tranſlations; Mr.
<hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leil,</hi> in his booke that Chriſt deſcended not in to hell, pag.
116. ſaith: that they haue depraued the ſenſe, obſcured the truth, &amp; deceaued the ignorant, that in many places they do detort the ſcriptures from the right ſenſe, they shew themſelues to loue darkneſſe more then light, falshood more then truth. The
<hi>Miniſters</hi> of <hi>Lincolue</hi> dioceſſe in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridgement of their booke to his Maieſtie, giue their like publique teſtimony, tearming the English tranſlation, that taketh away from the text, that addeth to the text, &amp;c. a tranſlation which is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd and ſenſleſſe. And the
<hi>Puritanes</hi> in their peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his Maieſty pag. 76. do charge the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of the Pſalmes to differ from the truth of the Hebrew in addition, ſubſtraction, &amp; alteration in 200. places at the leaſt: in ſo much as they do therefore profeſſe to reſt doubtfull, whether a man with a ſafe conſcience may ſubſcribe therunto. Not without cauſe did his Maieſty therefore affirme in the conference before him pag. 46. that he could neuer yet ſee a Bible well tranſlated in English. And
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:18148:46"/> as our learned aduerſaries do thus agree to diſagree in their owne tranſlations mutually condemning each other, ſo alſo haue they vpon a ſecond and more due conſideration afforded honorable teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony euen of our vulgar Latin tranſlation had from Rome <hi>Beza annot. in</hi> 1 <hi>cap Luc. verſ.</hi> 1. ſaith: The old Interpreter, (meaning our Latine edition) ſeemeth to haue interpreted the holy bookes with meruailous ſinceritie and Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Conrad. praefat. in Pſalt. Couelin his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to Burges pag. 94.</note> The which reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious obſeruation is acknowledged by D. <hi>Humfrey</hi> de rat. interpret. pag.
74. by <hi>Carolus Molinaeus,</hi> by <hi>Conrardus Pelicanus,</hi> by D.
<hi>Couel,</hi> &amp; other Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>Wherefore iuſtly may we exclaime with <hi>S. Aug.</hi> cont.
<hi>Donatiſt.</hi> cap. 24. ſaying: <hi>O truth more forcible to wring out confeſsion, then is any rack or torment!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for ſo much, (moſt honorable Lordes and graue Lawiers) as it is the courſe of our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, vnder the deceiptfull vaile of this their ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, vncertaine, and doubtfull pretence of only ſcripture, to vndertake liberty of reiecting all proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes, and arguments drawne from the authority of all generall Councells, though neuer ſo ancient, neuer ſo vniuerſall, &amp; neuer ſo lawfully aſſembled; from the Iudgement and conſent of the Fathers, though neuer ſo learned, neuer ſo holy, and neur ſo ancient; from the practiſe of the Church though neuer ſo continuall neuer ſo agreable, neuer ſo <pb n="79" facs="tcp:18148:46"/> vniuerſall, and neuer ſo primitiue; And ſo therby in the end making themſelues, &amp; euery of their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers <hi>Iudges</hi> both of Scriptures, and of all Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters, reſtrayning all things to their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferring of places, which they can in their owne priuate opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, collect to be true; In ſo much that we may ſay with
<hi>S. Hierome Epiſt. ad Paulinum: Sola Scriptura ars eſt, quam ſibi paſsim omnes vendicant, hanc garrula anus, hanc delirus ſenex, hanc Sophiſta verboſus, hanc vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſi praeſumunt, lacerant, docent antequam diſcant.</hi> The Scripture only is an arte (or ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce) which euery one challengeth to themſelues, this the chatting old wife, this the doting oldman, this the prating So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſter, this euery body preſumes, rent, &amp; teach be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they learne. Againe writing againſt the <hi>Lucife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, tom.</hi> 3. he ſaith: <hi>Nec ſibi blandiantur, ſi de ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum capitulis videntur ſibi affimare quod dicunt, cum &amp; Diabolus de Scripturis aliqua ſit locutus, &amp; ſcripturae non in legendo, ſed intelligendo conſiſtant.</hi> Neither is this different from the publike doctrine thus decreed in the 20. article of their Religion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Church (ſay they) hath power to decree rites or ceremonies, &amp; authority in controuerſies of Faith.</p>
            <p>I appeale therfore to your learned Iudgemente, that if your temporall high Courte &amp; parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te be of ſuch force, that men are to reſt &amp; rely on the Iudgement giuen, and ſentence once pronounced,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:18148:47"/> our ſpirituall high Courts of Generall, Nationall, and Prouinciall Councells, vnitie of the Church, and conſent of the Fathers, be any waies inferiour to your temporall high courts, and to haue no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, no force, to giue out Iudgment, pronounce ſentence, and decide controuerſies, ſo that no writ of errour or appeale lieth, wherby to ſupport the party ſo conuicted in the further humor of his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied &amp; endleſſe contention.</p>
            <p>And to omit much other correſpondence that may be alleaged, and applied euen to your owne principles, not to ſeeme offenſiue or tedious, we will here briefly inſinuate ſome other proofes, of no leſſe force then the precedents.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="section">
            <head>SECTION X. <hi>OTHER PROOFES.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>OVCHſafe therfore, (Graue &amp; learned) to adde vnto that, which hath bene ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, the anſwerable doctrine of theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, &amp; ancient Iewes, (who liued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſts coming) foretelling &amp; writing (by ſpeciall inſtinct) concerning our Cath. Church, and B. Sacrifice commonly termed the Maſſe, &amp; that ſo plainly, that as
<hi>Galatinus</hi> a learned catholike <pb n="81" facs="tcp:18148:47"/> in his, <hi>arcanis Catholicae veritatis,</hi> lib. 2. cap. 3. affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, they may be thought not ſo much to haue foretould things to come, as to haue reported Euangelicall things already done. To this end ſaith <hi>Rabbi Cahana:</hi> The
<hi>Sacrifice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rabbi Cahana ad cap. 49. Gen. Verſ.
2.</note> which shalbe offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of wine, shall not only be changed into the ſubſtance of the blood of the <hi>Meſsias,</hi> but alſo into the ſubſtance of his body. The Sacrifice, which shalbe of bread, notwithſtanding that it be white as milke, shalbe conuerted into the ſubſtance of the body of the <hi>Meſsias.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rabbi Iudas,</note> In like manner <hi>Rabbi Iudas</hi> in 23. Exod. ſaith: The bread shalbe changed, when it shalbe ſacrificed, from the ſubſtance of bread in to the ſubſtance of the body of the <hi>Meſsias,</hi> who shall deſcend from heauen, &amp; he himſelf shalbe the ſacrifice. <hi>Rabbi Simeon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rabbi Simeon.</note> ſaith: <hi>in libro de reuelatione ſecretorum: The Sacrifice, which after the Meſsias his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, Prieſts ſhall make, &amp;c.</hi> they shall make it of bread &amp; wine, &amp;c. and that ſacrifice, which shalbe celebrated vpon euery altar, shalbe turned into the body of the <hi>Meſsias. Rabbi Barachias in Eccleſiaſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rabbi Barach.</note> teacheth, that at the comming of the <hi>Meſsias</hi> food shall come from heauen litle a like cake; This ſame is affirmed by <hi>Rabbi Ionathas</hi> lib. collect. in Pſal. 72.<note place="margin">Rabbi Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thas. Rabbi Moſes.</note> and
<hi>Rabbi Hardarſan</hi> in Pſal. 136. &amp; alſo by others alleadged by
<hi>Petrus Galatinus de arcanis Catholicae ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis.</hi> Theſe
<hi>Rabbines</hi> affirme likewiſe, that <hi>Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedechs</hi> offering of bread &amp; wine in ſacrifice, was a <pb n="82" facs="tcp:18148:48"/> prefiguration of that Sacrifice, which was to be offered after the <hi>Meſsias</hi> his comming. So <hi>Rabbi Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> in <hi>Bereſchith</hi> in cap. 14.<note place="margin">Rabbi Samuel.</note> 
               <hi>Geneſ.</hi> auerreth, ſaying:
<hi>Mechiſedech</hi> ſet forth the actes of Prieſthood, for he ſacrificed bread &amp; wine to the Holy God.<note place="margin">Rabbi Phinees</note> 
               <hi>Rabbi Phinees ibidem,</hi> ſaith: In the time of the
<hi>Meſsias</hi> all ſacrifice shall ceaſe, but the ſacrifice of bread and wine shall not ceaſe, &amp;c. As it is ſayd Pſal. 110. <hi>Thou art a Prieſt for euer according to the Order of Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech.</hi> Theſame affirmeth <hi>Rabbi Moyſes Hardarſan, ibid.</hi> in cap. 14.
<hi>Geneſ</hi> This point is ſo euident in the old <hi>Iewiſh Rabbins,</hi> that <hi>Theodorus Bibliander,</hi> (a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant of great fame) lib. 2. de SS. Trinit. pag. 89. doubted not accordingly to confeſſe theſame; In ſo much alſo as the ancient Fathers of the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church are likewiſe by our learned aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, (as Mr. <hi>Fulk</hi> againſt
<hi>Heskins</hi> pag. 99. <hi>Andreas Craſtonius, de opific. Miſſae,</hi> lib. 1. pag. 28. ſect. 66. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to haue belieued accordingly the foreſaid ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of <hi>Melchiſedech.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither are the Prophets wanting in this point foretelling a Prieſthood and ſacrifice; and theſame, not the offering vpon the Croſſe, which is now an acte of Sacrifice tranſitory &amp; paſt, but to continue for euer; and not in bloudy manner, but according to the order of
<hi>Melchiſedech.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 10. Malach. ca. 1.10.</note> So the Prophet <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachy</hi> fore shewing the reiecting of the Legall Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood <pb n="83" facs="tcp:18148:48"/> &amp; ſacrifice, foretelleth of the now
<hi>Sacrifice</hi> of the Chriſtian Gentiles to ſucceed, which he termeth
<hi>a cleane Oblation;</hi> which is the Sacrifice of the Maſſe. The Prophet <hi>Daniell</hi> fore shewing likewiſe the end of the world &amp;
<hi>Antichriſts</hi> comming,<note place="margin">Dan. ca. 12.11.</note> foretelleth in like manner that as then the daily Sacrifice shalbe taken away; which one Sacrifice cannot be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the many ſpirituall ſacrifices of praier &amp; thankeſgiuing; for that <hi>Antichriſts</hi> perſecution shall rather increaſe, then take theſe away. Neither can
<hi>Malachies</hi> prediction of that <hi>one Oblation</hi> be taken to ſignifie thoſe ſaid ſpirituall ſacrifices, becauſe that they are many, and but improperly called Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, or were not new or peculiar only to the Gentills, but were alſo belonging to thoſe of the old Teſtament, no leſſe then now are to vs, Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, inuocation, Pſalmes, Feſtiuall daies, faſting, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes deedes, &amp; the like. The Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> foretel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Eccleſiaſticall Miniſters of the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment termeth them <hi>Prieſts,</hi> which hath relation to a ſacrifice.</p>
            <p>More ouer the wordes of the Euangeliſt <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.28.
<hi>Mar</hi> 14.24. <hi>Luk</hi> 22.19.20. And of <hi>S. Paul.</hi> 1.
<hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24. are literally anſwerable hereunto, ſaying: not that, which <hi>(ſhalbe) giuen</hi> or offered; but, which <hi>(is)</hi> giuen: and not <hi>(to you,)</hi> but <hi>(for you;)</hi> the Greeke being the preſent tenſe in all the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, <pb n="84" facs="tcp:18148:49"/> and in <hi>S. Pauls epiſt.</hi> ſpeaking of the body, and in <hi>S. Luke</hi> alſo in the Latine; &amp; our aduerſaries the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſo put it in their tranſlations.<note place="margin">Heb. 13.10.</note> The Apoſtle to his effect called our table <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar for ſacrifice.<note place="margin">Ignat.</note> A word vſed by <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles vndoubted Scoller in his Epiſt. ad Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delp. by
<hi>Nazianzenus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nazian.</note> 
               <hi>in oratione pro Gorgonia.</hi> By <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſo.</note>
               <hi>in demonſtrat. quod Chriſtus ſit Deus,</hi> &amp; by <hi>S. Auſtine Epiſt.</hi> 86.<note place="margin">Aug.</note> and that in a very proper ſenſe to ſacrifice Chriſts body vpon, and ſo called of them in reſpect of the ſaid body ſacrificed.</p>
            <p>Fourtly this is euident by the inſtitution of the Euchariſte it ſelfe: for Chriſt commanded his Apoſtles, &amp; in them there Succeſſours, to do the ſame which he did: But he did truely ſacrifice, as performing the office of a Prieſt according to the order of
<hi>Melchiſed.</hi> King of <hi>Salem,</hi> who offered vp bread and wine: Therefore neceſſary it was, that Chriſt should inſtitute an vnbloudy ſacrifice vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the formes of bread &amp; wine, and that to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in his Church vntill the worlds end, becauſe he otherwiſe could not be truely ſaid to be a Prieſt for euer; for Prieſt, &amp; Sacrifice cannot be aſunder: Neither is he Prieſt, that hath no Sacrifice to offer vp as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">Heb. 5.8</note> and ſeing the ſacrifice of the Croſſe was to be performed as once, and cannot be againe repeated, it muſt follow conſequently, that <pb n="85" facs="tcp:18148:49"/> there is in the Church ſome other ſacrifice, which Chriſt the high Prieſt may be ſaid to offer by his Miniſters for euer; which can be no other then the Sacrifice of the Maſſe, once offered vp by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf inſtituting the Euchariſte, and now by his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</p>
            <p>Fiftly ſeing the figures of the old teſtament, as the Paſchall Lambe, the bloud of the Teſtament, &amp; generally all the ſacrifice of the old law, were, (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the vniforme doctrine of all the ancient Fathers) ſignes and figures of the Euchariſte: But they were truely Sacrifices: therefore the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſte no leſſe: otherwiſe it should follow the figures to haue bene more perfect, then the things figured.</p>
            <p>Sixtly,<note place="margin">Act. 4.</note> If Miracles in all ages haue bene of great force to confirme true doctrine, (as we may ſee in our Sauiour &amp; in his Apoſtles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) ſo that <hi>S. Aug.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. cont. ep. Manich. cap. 4 &amp; lib. 8. de Ciuit. Dei.</note> pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth theſame among theſe things, which moſt iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly held him in the Churches beſome: Then, who will but read the Fathers, shall find them plentifull euen in Miracles wrought in confirmation of the Sacrifice of the Maſſe. <hi>S. Auſtine</hi> reporteth of his owne time and countrey;<note place="margin">Aug. de Cant. Dei lib. 22. cap. 8.</note> how that one
<hi>Heſperius</hi> hauing his houſe infeſted with wicked Spirites, to the affliction of his beaſts, &amp; ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, deſired, (ſaith <hi>S. Auſtine</hi>) in my abſence certaine of our Prieſtes, that ſome would go thither, &amp;c. one went, and <pb n="86" facs="tcp:18148:50"/> offered there, (ſaith he) the Sacrificie of the body of Chriſt, praying what he might, that the vexation the might ceaſe; &amp; God being therupon mercifull, it ceaſed.<note place="margin">Chryſ. Greg.</note> In like manner <hi>S. Chryſoſtome lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Sacerd. S. Gregorij lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Mor.</hi> and <hi>S. Bede hiſt. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 22. do report ſundry miracles to this ſame effect.</p>
            <p>Seauently reaſon, &amp; nature do confirme this; For Religion &amp; Sacrifice are ſo conioyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the one cannot be without the other; for neuer was there yet any nation in the world, that had not ſome kinde of Religion and worhipping, and that did not thinke Sacrifice neceſſary to the worship of God, ſeing Sacrifice is the higheſt exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall worship, that can be exhibited by man to God, for, things are more excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t then wordes, ſpecially whoſe ſubſtance is conſumed vpon Gods honor. But certainly the vniuerſall conſent of all nations proceedeth from the inſtinct of nature.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the more ſober and learned ſort of our aduerſaries do afford to vs Catholikes the hopefull promiſes of ſaluation, affirming this to be the iudgment of all learned Proteſtants: as D. <hi>Some</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth in his defence againſt <hi>Penry</hi> the <hi>Puritane,</hi> pag.
176.<note place="margin">D. Som. Couell.</note> This ſame auerreth Mr.
<hi>Couell</hi> in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> pag 68. accuſing his brethren that affirme the contrary,<note place="margin">Caſſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</note> of ignorant zeale. <hi>Georg. Caſſander lib. de officio pij viri,</hi> pag.
14. ſaith: The <pb n="87" facs="tcp:18148:50"/> Church of Rome is to be reuerenced, as being the true Church and temple of God.<note place="margin">Hooker.</note> Mr.
<hi>Hooker</hi> lib. 5. pag. 188. ſaith in his Eccl. Policij: that the Church of Rome is to be reputed a part of the houſe of God, a limme of the viſible Church of Chriſt, &amp;c. So ſaith Mr. <hi>Bunney</hi> in his Treatiſe ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to pacification, ſect. 8. pag 109.<note place="margin">Bunney. Baro. Morton</note> So Mr. <hi>Baro</hi> in one of his ſermons; ſerm. 3. So Mr.
<hi>Morton</hi> in his Treatiſe of the kingdome of Iſrael, &amp; of the Church, pag. 94. So Mr. <hi>Field</hi> in his Treatiſe of the Church lib. 3. cap. 46. And Mr. <hi>Couell</hi> in his treatiſe pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished by authority, &amp; dedicated to the Lo. Arch. of Canterbury, defended this opinion at large, and concludeth ſaying: <hi>VVee affirme them of the Church of Rome to be parts of the Church of Chriſt, and that tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, that liue and die in that Church may not withſtanding be ſaued.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>SECTION XI.</hi> A DISCOVERY OF CONTRARY doctrine.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS then (Right honorable, Reuerend, Graue, and learned) being our confeſſed Religion &amp; Catholike doctrine, &amp; thus made ſo euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by ſo many conuincing <pb n="88" facs="tcp:18148:51"/> arguments, &amp; irrefragable proofes: I am now like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe moſt humbly to intreate you, not to ſeeme of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue or tedious, if alſo I make bould to put your Wiſedomes in remembrance, by what inſtinct this ſoo generally confirmed, receaued, &amp; continued do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Maſſe it ſelfe, (become as now to you ſo odious, &amp; to vs by your lawes ſo penall) hath bene now of late ſo impugned &amp; traduced. The principall man &amp; moſt notorious was an Apoſtata Monke <hi>Martin Luther,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luther. Whitak. in reſp. ad rat. Campi. Iewell in his def. pag. 426. Alberus contra Carol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtadia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos. Powell in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. Luther tom. 7. Witte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b. an. 1558. lib. de Miſſa priuata fol. 443</note> whome Proteſtants reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and name their Father, and a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t man, ſent of God to lighten the whole world, and whome the <hi>Lutherans</hi> gloriouſly vaunt to haue bene the firſt, that impugned the Maſſe. Mr. <hi>Powell</hi> a Proteſtant writer termeth him, holy <hi>S. Luther.</hi> But by what inſtinction or genius, from what ground worke, (I pray you) it was, which ſo directed <hi>Luther</hi> to impugne the Maſſe: not by any other, but by the ſuggeſtion and perſwaſion of <hi>Sathan,</hi> (with whoſe affrighting and apparitions he had bene in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted from his youth:) For it chanced, that vpon a certaine time, (as himſelf reporteth the matter) he was ſodainly awaked about midnight, then (ſaith he) <hi>Sathan</hi> began this diſputation with me, ſaying: Hearken right learned Doctor <hi>Luther,</hi> thou haſt celebrated priuate Maſſe the ſpace of 15. yeares &amp;c. And ſo the Deuill with arguments, (which <pb n="89" facs="tcp:18148:51"/> 
               <hi>Luther</hi> himſelf there at large ſetteth downe) endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoring to diſſuade
<hi>Luther,</hi> any more to ſay Maſſe: but as yet <hi>Luther</hi> ſtanding in defence therof, iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying to the Deuill his ſaying of Maſſe.<note place="margin">Tom. 7. Witte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b. of anno 1558 fol. 229.</note> But (ſaith <hi>Luther) Sathan</hi> replied more vehemently, &amp;c. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon in the end <hi>Luther</hi> yeldeth, and embraceth the doctrine ſo deliuered by
<hi>Sathan,</hi> &amp; ther vpon now altogether abandoneth the Maſſe. This is confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly defended euen by <hi>Luthers</hi> deareſt Scollers, as
<hi>Hoſpinianus in hiſtor. Sacram<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fol.</hi> 131. <hi>part. altera:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſpin. Io. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius.</note> 
               <hi>Ioan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Regius conſiderat. cenſurae, pag.</hi> 123. Neither was this conference betweene the Deuill &amp; <hi>Luther</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall only, or a dreame; but as <hi>Balduinus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baldui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> (a fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower of
<hi>Luther</hi> lib. de diſput. <hi>Luther</hi> cap. 4. pag. 83.) ſaith: a reall truth written by <hi>Luther</hi> (ſaith he) not hyperbolically, but ſeriouſly, and according to the truth of the hiſtory. And if we looke to
<hi>Luthers</hi> life after his Apoſtacie, we shall find it anſwerable to his doctrine, both tending to libertie; it needeth not any other teſtimonie, then that, which the Proteſtants themſelues acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: For (ſay they)
<hi>Luther</hi> became ſo arrogant,<note place="margin">Ioac. Camar. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ugio Lutheri. Conrad. Regius de caena Dom.</note> inſolent, and poſſeſſed with the ſinne of Pride, that God therefore did withdraw his true ſpiritt from him. This we may manifeſtly gather out of his owne writings, Tom. 2, Germ. Fol. 9. &amp; praefat. lib. de abrog. Miſſ. where he acknowledged his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience <pb n="90" facs="tcp:18148:52"/> accuſing him, &amp; condemning him of ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity againſt the whole Chriſtian world, all times, places, perſons, and authorities; Theſe be his owne wordes: how often hath my heart panted &amp; repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended me obiecting againſt me! what? art thou only wiſe? can it be credible, that all others do erre, &amp; haue erred ſo long time? haue all generations ſo often euer bene deceaued? What if thou doſt erre, &amp; bring ſo many into errour, that shalbe damned for euer? art thou only he, which hath the true pure word of God? Hath no man in the world theſame but thou? that, which the Church of Chriſt hath hitherto defined, and ſo many yeares obſerued as good, doſt thou ouerthrow it, as though it were euill, &amp; ſo doſt diſsipate by thy doctrine both Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, &amp; ciuill common weales? Thus his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, ſo long as he had any, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned him, thus he repented his diſobedience, and ſaid, (<hi>in praef. in tom.</hi> 1. <hi>Germ. Ientacul.</hi>) that he hoped the bookes which he had written, would be burnt &amp; infect no more; but when the bridle of Obedience was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together broken, his conſcience extinguished, and the plumes of pride, &amp; ſenſualitie had mounted ſo high, and carried him ſo farre, he behaued himſelf in his apoſtacie,<note place="margin">Suet.</note> as by the teſtimonie of <hi>Suetonius (in vita Iul. Caeſ.) Iulius Caeſar</hi> did in his temporall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt the
<hi>Roman ſtate;</hi> who in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <pb n="91" facs="tcp:18148:52"/> doubted, whether he should go forward, or no;<note place="margin">Luther in col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loq. Menſal. fol. 241. Tom 5. Germ. 121. Oſiand. cent. 13. lib. 1. cap. 4. pag.
329 The ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. writers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cent. 13. cap. 5. Fulk. in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue. pag 124. Mela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ct. loc. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. de po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſt. Whitak. cap. 18. Oſiand. Epiſt. cent. 16. pag. 86. Conrad. in Theol Calui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt in proaem.</note> but when he had caſt of shame, he brake out into this ſpeech <hi>Iacta eſt alea:</hi> my chance is throwne. So <hi>Luther</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> shipwracke was made of shamefaſtnes, vttered his vnreaſonable reſolution of obſtinate perſiſting in theſe termes: Becauſe, (ſaith he) I haue entred into this cauſe, now I muſt looke vnto it, &amp; of neceſsity ſay, it is iuſt: If you aske a reaſon, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Martin Luther</hi> will haue it ſo: <hi>ſic volo, ſic iubeo, ſit pro ratione voluntas.</hi> And thus much briefly of <hi>Sathans</hi> labouring by the miniſtry of <hi>Luther</hi> to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne the Maſſe, and neuer knowne to haue bene in any age before impugned, otherwiſe then by the <hi>Albigenſes, Apostolici, Almericus, VVickliffs,</hi> and ſuch other, as in regard of their other opinions, were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly euen in the Iudgment of our very aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries all of them noted, &amp; knowne heretikes: whoſe opinions in this, &amp; other particulars were priuate, &amp; by the ſaid parties afterwards recanted &amp; called backe, or elſe died with them. And as for <hi>Caroloſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius,</hi> &amp; <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temporanean to <hi>Luther,</hi> (whome Proteſtants name brethren) their proceedings to impugne the Maſſe, was not different from that of <hi>Luthers,</hi> viz: by illuſions of
<hi>Sathan,</hi> as Proteſtants themſelues do with diſlike report of them
<hi>Luther</hi> in loc com claſſ. 5 pag 47. ſpeaking of
<hi>Caroloſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius,</hi> calleth him a man giuen ouer into a reprobate
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:18148:53"/> ſenſe; and of <hi>Zuinglius</hi> he ſaith, he condemned &amp; auoyded him with all his hart, as deſpayring of his ſaluation, as <hi>Hoſpinianus</hi> witneſſeth in hiſtor. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cram. part.<note place="margin">Whitak. contra camp. rat. 8.</note> alt. pag. 187. And the ſame they thinke of <hi>Luther.</hi> So well agree the Fathers, &amp; the Brethren as Proteſtants call them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>SECTION XII.</hi> THE CONCLVSION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>ARDON me therefore, (Right honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Reuerend, &amp; learned) if I be ſo bould now to appeale to your <hi>VViſedomes</hi> graue and mature Iudgement:<note place="margin">Vt ſup.</note> whether <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> doctrine concerning the Maſſe, which had its growth in this age by apparitions from the <hi>Deuill,</hi> (as him ſelf &amp; his deareſt Schollers do accordingly confeſſe) be of greater credit &amp; authority, then that doctrine &amp; Religion, whoſe vndoubted proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes are anſwerable &amp; correſpondent to the like re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued principles &amp; groundes of your owne lawes: then that Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which remaineth in it ſelf beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with manifold &amp; confeſſed ornaments from ancient and memorable teſtimonies of your owne nation, of all Chriſtian nations, &amp; of all precedent times: then that Religion, whereto the English <pb n="93" facs="tcp:18148:53"/> nation was in the Apoſtles times confeſſedly firſt conuerted: Then that Religion, which hath foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded your ancient municipall lawes and courts of iudgement, erected your Churches, Bishops-ſeas, Religious houſes, Colledges, Vniuerſities, and many other knowne monuments of pietie: Then that Religion, to which ſo many Kings &amp; Kingdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of Gentils haue bene conuerted according to the ſundry plaine praedictions of the Prophets, had in that behalfe of Chriſts true Church, which ſaid praedictions otherwiſe then in, &amp; by this Religion are yet hitherto co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſedly left vnperformed. Then that Religion, whoſe Prieſthood and ſacrifice was foretould by the Prophetes, and acknowledged by the Apoſtles. Then that Religion, which is anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to the doctrine of thoſe Religious Iewes, who liued before Chriſt: Then that Religion, which euen then long ſince was vniuerſally profeſſed in the Chriſtian world: Then that Religion, in which was then alſo confirmed to vs from heauen with teſtimony of vndoubted miracles: Then that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion &amp; Faith, approued of by the conſent of ſo many Generall, Nationall, and Prouinciall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, by the Iudgment of ſo many holy, learned, &amp; ancient Fathers practiſe of all times, and ages, and euen by the confeſsion of our aduerſaries: Then that Religion, againſt which all Sects &amp; hereſies <pb n="94" facs="tcp:18148:54"/> whatſoeuer, (howſoeuer deuided otherwiſe amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt themſelues) do yet generally conſpire: Then that Religion, to which our aduerſaries afford to the members &amp; Profeſſours, therof the hopefull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of ſaluation: Then that Religion, which only is ratified by all authoritie, all Scriptures, Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Prophetes, &amp; Sibills Rabbins before Chriſt, by the Apoſtles, Euangeliſts, all holy &amp; learned Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Hiſtorians, Antiquaries, and Monuments, all Sinods, Councels, lawes, Parliaments, Canons, &amp; decrees of Popes, Emperors, Kings, &amp; Rulers; all Martyrs, Confeſſors, and holy Witneſſes; by all Friends &amp; Enemies, euen Mahometans, Iewes, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, infidells, all former Heretikes, Schiſmatikes, and theſe Proteſtants themſelues, when they were moſt probable to ſpeake truth; and all Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies that can be deuiſed, not only in this world, but of God, of Angells, and glorified ſoules, whoſe euidence cannot be vntrue; of deuills and damned ſoules in hell condemned for their contempt, or negligence thereof; of ſoules in Purgatorie, and whatſoeuer can be cited for witneſſe in ſuch caſes, as is moſt euident in this brief treatiſe.</p>
            <p>In reſpect whereof, your knowne Wiſedomes in other matters, cannot be wanting, or tranſported herein with generall preiudice of our cauſe; but obſeruing your owne principles, and abandoning
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:18148:54"/> all preiudice of opinion, try the ſpirits if they be of God, and proue all things, houlding that which is good, as <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſaith in his 4. <hi>Chapt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the reading therefore &amp; carefull examinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this our
<hi>Application</hi> do we humbly requeſt you, and that by the tender care had of your countrey, by the deare reſpect of your ſaluation, by your Chriſtian zeale vnto true Religion, &amp; by whatſoeuer elſe is ſacred and holy,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your poore Countryman. <hi>M.E.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:18148:55"/>
            <head>A TABLE OF THE SEVERALL points handled in this treatiſe, diuided in to 12 Sections as followeth.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>The firſt Section.</label>THe lawe tearmes, in generall peruſed in this Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. pag. <hi>1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 2.</label> A verdict conſiſting of twelue generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells, all of them being within the first <hi>400.</hi> &amp; odde yeares after our Sauiour Chriſt. pag. <hi>5.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 3.</label> The teſtimony of twelue lawfull &amp; credible witneſſes. pag. <hi>14.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 4.</label> The Confeſsion of twelue of the leardeneſt of the aduerſary party. pag. <hi>25.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 5.</label> Of Priority of Poſſeſsion. pag.
<hi>41.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 6.</label> Of Preſcription. pag.
<hi>56.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 7.</label> Of Continuall Claime. pag.
<hi>61.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 8.</label> Of the doubtfulneſſe of the ſtatute law. pag. <hi>69.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 9.</label> Of high courtes of Iudgment. pag.
<hi>73.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 10.</label> Other Proofes. pag <hi>80.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 11.</label> A diſcouery of the contrary doctrine. pag. <hi>87.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 12.</label>
               </item>
               <item>The Concluſion. pag. <hi>92.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18148:55"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
